جد	SCP	O
کہ	SC	O
ساڈی	PRS	O
لوک	JJ	O
بولی	NN	O
اکو	CD	O
ہڑپے	JJ	O
مہراں	NN	O
پا	VBF	O
صراف	NNP	O
دیکھال	PSP	O
ایہناں	PDM	O
بعد	NN	O
آے	VBF	O
ایتھے	NN	O
آریہ	NN	O
کہندے	VBF	O
ہن	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
آن	VBI	O
توں	PSP	O
پہلاں	NN	O
ایتھے	NN	O
پنج	CD	O
نسلی	JJ	O
گروہ	NN	O
وسدے	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

سبھ	Q	O
کجھ	Q	O
اوسے	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
دتا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کسے	PDM	O
ہور	JJ	O
ملک	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
خفیاں	JJ	O
فائلاں	NN	O
بارے	PSP	O
کجھ	Q	O
نہیں	NEG	O
کہیا	VBF	O
جا	AUXA	O
سکتا	AUXM	O
۔	PU	O

کجھ	Q	O
لوک	NN	O
ایہو	PRP	O
جہے	PRR	O
وی	PRT	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
جہڑے	PRR	O
پچھلی	JJ	O
عمر	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رفاہی	JJ	O
کماں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
زندگی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
حصہ	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
لیندے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
وچ	PSP	O
زندگی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
باقی	JJ	O
حصا	NN	O
لنگھا	VBF	O
دیندے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جے	SCP	O
ایوب	NNP	PER
خان	NN	PER
مارشلاء	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
لاندا	VBF	O
اتے	SC	O
رواجی	JJ	O
طریقے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
جنوری	NNP	O
وچ	PSP	O
اعلان	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
مطابق	NN	O
چوناں	NN	O
ہوجاندیاں	VBF	O
تاں	SC	O
اسمبلیاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تصفیہہ	NN	O
ہوجانا	VBI	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ہن	NN	O
میں	PRP	O
روندی	VBF	O
پھردی	VBF	O
آں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ٹھیک	JJ	O
ہے	VBF	O
سرکاری	JJ	O
ملازم	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
وچوں	PSP	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
ہن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کراچی	NNP	LOC
دی	PSP	O
کمیونسٹ	NN	O
پارٹی	NN	O
تے	CC	O
بنگلہ	JJ	O
دیش	NN	O
بناون	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
قرار	NN	O
داد	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
منظور	NN	O
کیتے	VBF	O
بیٹھے	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
اس	PRP	O
نیں	PSP	O
کدی	NN	O
کشمیریاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
آزادی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
گل	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
کیتی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کیوں	RB	O
جے	SC	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
اجتماعی	JJ	O
شعور	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
تاریخی	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
ثقافتی	JJ	O
تانے	NN	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
نالوں	PSP	O
ٹٹ	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
تاریخی	JJ	O
ثقافتی	JJ	O
عمل	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
نتیجے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
پورپ	NNP	O
پار	NN	O
چلے	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

نکے	JJ	O
بال	NN	O
باراں	CD	O
نمبر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ڈور	NN	O
لے	VBF	O
جاندے	AUXA	O
رہے	AUXP	O
تے	CC	O
وڈی	JJ	O
عمراں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
بندے	NN	O
گڈے	JJ	O
پتنگاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

جگا	PRT	PER
میرے	PRS	O
بچیاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
خرچ	NN	O
دیندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

چپ	NN	O
تے	CC	O
اداس	JJ	O
موٹیاں	JJ	O
اکھاں	NN	O
،	PU	O
سنگھ	NNP	O
اتانہہ	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ولے	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

میرے	PRS	O
متھے	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
چوٹ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
نشان	NN	O
دیکھ	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
ایں	AUXT	O
نا	PRT	O
؟	PU	O

شہر	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
گل	NN	O
دھم	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

جرنیلی	JJ	O
سڑک	NN	O
اپڑکے	VBF	O
اوہ	PRP	O
مڑدے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کریم	NN	LOC
پورے	JJ	LOC
دا	PSP	O
گشت	NN	O
شروع	NN	O
کردے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پھیر	RB	O
کھوتا	NN	O
اچی	JJ	O
واج	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ڈھینچوں	NN	O
ڈھینچوں	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
مونہہ	NN	O
اگے	NN	O
سپیکر	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
مائیک	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دیندے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

کوئی	PRP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
ہتھ	NN	O
مکھی	NN	O
اڈاون	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
ہلدا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
ایسے	PRP	O
طرحاں	PSP	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
پیر	NN	O
اجے	NN	O
پتھر	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	AUXT	O
ہوئے	VBF	O
لگدے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

‫	FF	O
توں	PSP	O
بعد	NN	O
ہیر	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
کہانی	NN	O
اے‫	VBF	O
کول	PSP	O
دمودر	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
پہچان	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
طبیعت	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ضدی	JJ	O
ضرور	RB	O
اے	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
دل	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بھیڑا	JJ	O
بالکل	RB	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

تھیڑ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
بہت	Q	O
ادمی	JJ	O
سی	VBF	O
بال	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
سن	VBF	O
اساں	PRP	O
سبھ	Q	O
کجھ	Q	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اپروں	NN	O
ویکھن	VBI	O
وچ	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
خاص	JJ	O
گل	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
لگدی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
آپنی	APNA	O
بے	JJ	O
وسی	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
غصہ	NN	O
جہیا	PRT	O
آیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پچھلے	JJ	O
مہینے	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
اوس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
بچپن	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
سردل	NN	O
ٹپ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
جوانی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ویڑھے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
قدم	NN	O
رکھیا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
مینوں	PRP	O
نویں	JJ	O
چنتا	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
آگھیریا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
دھی	NN	O
جوان	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

شمائلہ	NNP	PER
رب	NNP	O
توں	PSP	O
بعد	NN	O
ماں	NN	O
اوہ	PDM	O
ہستی	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
جس	PRR	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
انسان	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
جڑت	NN	O
جسمانی	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
روحانی	JJ	O
طور	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
سب	Q	O
توں	PSP	O
چوکھی	Q	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

دھڑت	JJ	O
دلالی	NN	O
ویدگی	NN	O
آہندے	VBF	O
پہلوں	NN	O
لے	VBF	O
چکا	AUXA	O
کم	NN	O
کرا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
آدمی	NN	O
مگروں	PSP	O
دیندے	VBF	O
جھگڑا	NN	O
پا	VBF	O
مارن	VBI	O
گیا	AUXA	O
سو	CD	O
مر	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
آہندے	VBF	O
مارن	VBI	O
مول	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
جا	VBF	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
ہور	Q	O
حملہ	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جیس	PRR	O
توں	PSP	O
آصف	NNP	PER
انکاری	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
گورت	JJ	O
دعوی	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
ثبوت	NN	O
منگدی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
تاں	PRT	O
حالے	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
اوس	PRP	O
نال	PSP	O
ناراض	JJ	O
سن	VBF	O
اندروں	NN	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
خاندان	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
حالے	NN	O
تک	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
ڈائیورس	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	AUXT	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سہوترابہتا	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
مینوں	PRP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
پتہ	NN	O
پرپیسہ	JJ	O
نظر	NN	O
آون	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہدی	PRS	O
خیر	NN	O
بڑی	JJ	O
بھیڑی	JJ	O
ہونی	VBI	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

خالد	NNP	PER
چنگا	JJ	O
منڈا	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
افسوس	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
گل	NN	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
وے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
انسان	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
زنخوں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
اولاد	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
میں	PRP	O
تکشک	NN	O
ناگن	NN	O
ورگی	PRR	O
سوہنی	JJ	O
غصیلی	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
آن	Q	O
بان	NN	O
والی	VALA	O
کڑی	NN	O
ایہو	PRP	O
جیہے	PRR	O
منڈے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ویاہ	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
سوچ	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سکدی	AUXM	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
سمجھاو	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
میرا	PRS	O
پچھا	NN	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
دیوے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

کافی	Q	O
دیر	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
سوچدی	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
۔	PU	O

ساڈے	PRS	O
اخبار	NN	O
ملین	CD	O
تے	PSP	O
بلین	CD	O
وچ	PSP	O
جدوں	NN	O
رقماں	NN	O
لکھدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	SC	O
عوام	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
گل	NN	O
لکائی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کلاسک	JJ	O
بابا	NN	PER
فرید	NNP	PER
کہے	VBF	O
فرید	NNP	PER
بھگت	NNP	O
کبیر	NNP	O
نانک	NNP	O
بانی	NNP	O
کلام	NN	O
نانک	NNP	O
کافیاں	NN	O
شاہ	NNP	PER
حسین	NNP	PER
سنگت	NN	O
شاہ	NNP	PER
حسین	NNP	PER
ابیات	NN	O
سلطان	NNP	PER
باہو	NNP	PER
مرزا	NN	PER
صاحباں	NNP	PER
۔	PU	O

میریاں	PRS	O
نظراں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سوال	NN	O
محسوس	NN	O
کردی	VBF	O
اوہ	PDM	O
بولی	NN	O
معلوم	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہوون	VBI	O
گے	AUXT	O
پیجی	VBF	PER
پرویز	NNP	PER
اوہدا	PRS	O
بھرا	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
لفنگے	JJ	O
یار	NN	O
کھانے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
میز	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
دوجے	OD	O
دی	PSP	O
جانکاری	NN	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
احساس	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
اوہ	PRP	O
لفنگے	NN	O
تے	CC	O
بالکل	RB	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	VBF	O
چنگے	JJ	O
بھلے	JJ	O
ڈیشنگ	JJ	O
قسم	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
خوب	JJ	O
پڑھے	JJ	O
لکھے	JJ	O
منڈے	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
خالد	NNP	PER
نال	PSP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
میری	PRS	O
پہلی	OD	O
ملاقات	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سارے	JJ	O
ای	PRT	O
کھڑے	VBF	O
بٹ	NN	O
بٹ	NN	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہدے	PRS	O
جتھے	NN	O
ڈھیر	Q	O
فیدے	NN	O
اوتھے	NN	O
اہندا	RB	O
غلط	JJ	O
ورتن	VBI	O
ایس	PDM	O
وسیب	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
گھن	VBF	O
لگ	VBF	O
جاون	AUXA	O
دی	PSP	O
طرح	PSP	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

آن	VBI	O
شاہی	JJ	O
محلے	NN	O
کنجریاں	NN	O
کول	PSP	O
ڈیرہ	NN	O
لایا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ہن	NN	O
اوتھے	NN	O
تسی	PRP	O
نہ	NEG	O
ڈھول	NN	O
وجا	VBF	O
سکدے	AUXM	O
اوہ	PRP	O
نہ	NEG	O
بھنگڑا	NN	O
پا	VBF	O
سکدے	AUXM	O
او	AUXT	O
نہ	NEG	O
اوہ	PRP	O
پوریاں	JJ	O
کر	VBF	O
سکدے	AUXM	O
اوہ	PRP	O
جیہناں	PRD	O
گلاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
تعلق	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
ایہناں	PDM	O
لوکاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
جد	NN	O
اپنے	APNA	O
ہوش	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
رہے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
باقی	JJ	O
دنیا	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
بارے	PSP	O
میں	PRP	O
کیہہ	RB	O
جاناں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
نال	PSP	O
سوال	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
جواب	NN	O
آون	VBI	O
توں	PSP	O
پہلاں	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
بوٹی	NN	O
چتھن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
جتن	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
اصلی	JJ	O
ناں	NN	O
کجھ	Q	O
ہور	Q	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

خالدکیہ	NNP	PER
ء	SYM	O
دیاں	PSP	O
چوناں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
مگروں	PSP	O
تنظیم	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
کیتا	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

مقامی	JJ	O
پدھر	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ویلا	NN	O
اپنی	APNA	O
چالے	NN	O
چل	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
ملن	VBI	O
اوہ	PRP	O
اٹلی	NNP	O
توں	PSP	O
بھارت	NNP	LOC
آئیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
کجھ	Q	O
دن	NN	O
پہلے	NN	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
خبراں	NN	O
کس	PDM	O
پہنچائیاں	VBF	O
جادوگراں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ڈیرا	NN	O
ہند	NNP	LOC
اندر	NN	O
جوتاں	NN	O
صدیاں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
جگائیاں	VBF	O
نے	PRX	O
ننگے	JJ	O
بدن	NN	O
تے	CC	O
تیڑ	JJ	O
لنگوٹیاں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
کھڑاواں	NN	O
لکڑی	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
پیریں	NN	O
پائیاں	VBF	O
نے	PRX	O
سکھاں	NN	O
واسطے	PSP	O
پت	NN	O
فقیر	NN	O
ہوئے	VBF	O
ماواں	NN	O
خبراں	NN	O
لین	VBI	O
نہ	NEG	O
آئیاں	VBF	O
نے	PRX	O
ایس	PRP	O
توں	PSP	O
اگے	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
کٹاس	RB	LOC
راج	NN	LOC
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
جدوں	NN	O
چاہوے	VBF	O
خالی	JJ	O
جھولی	NN	O
بھر	VBF	O
سکدا	AUXM	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

دنیا	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
وی	PRT	O
بولی	NN	O
مٹھی	JJ	O
کوڑی	JJ	O
اجڈ	JJ	O
یاں	CC	O
بھیڑی	JJ	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ء	SYM	O
دی	PSP	O
فلم	NN	O
دلا	NNP	O
بھٹی	NNP	O
وچ	PSP	O
زبیدہ	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
ہیروئن	NN	O
صبیحہ	NNP	O
دی	PSP	O
راز	NN	O
دار	JJ	O
سہیلی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کردار	NN	O
ادا	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

سلیم	NNP	PER
ہن	NN	O
توں	PRP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
لبھ	VBF	O
لے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PRP	O
توں	PSP	O
اگے	NN	O
سکولے	VBF	O
جان	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
ویلا	NN	O
آوندا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
جتھے	NN	O
اساڈا	PRS	O
واہ	NN	O
سکھن	VBI	O
دے	PSP	O
تریجے	OD	O
چوتھے	OD	O
انگاں	NN	O
پڑھن	VBI	O
تے	PSP	O
لکھن	VBI	O
نال	PSP	O
پیندا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اگوں	NN	O
کد	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
پئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PRP	O
طرحاں	PSP	O
کرن	VBI	O
والے	VALA	O
افسر	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
آکھیاتوں	VBF	O
میرے	PRS	O
توں	PSP	O
سچ	NN	O
چھپا	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
ایں	AUXT	O
تاں	SC	O
جو	PRR	O
میں	PRP	O
فکر	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
کراں	VBF	O
پرجد	INJ	O
اخیر	RB	O
مینوں	PRP	O
پتہ	NN	O
لگنا	VBI	O
ایں	AUXT	O
میں	PRP	O
ایس	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
پاروں	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
مر	VBF	O
جانا	AUXA	O
ایں	AUXT	O
پئی	SC	O
مینوں	PRP	O
اینے	Q	O
سچاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ساہمنا	NN	O
کرنا	VBI	O
پوے	AUXA	O
گا	AUXT	O
جیہڑے	PRR	O
مینوں	PRP	O
دسے	VBF	O
ای	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
گئے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ہور	Q	O
وی	PRT	O
کہانیاں	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
میری	PRS	O
کتاب	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

مدھیادیش	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
اوہ	PDM	O
تھاں	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جتھے	NN	O
سنسکرت	NNP	O
ایتھے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
بولی	NN	O
شور	NN	O
سینی	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
دھری	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
،	PU	O
کیوں	RB	O
جے	SC	O
سنسکرت	NNP	O
ادبی	JJ	O
بولی	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
ایس	PRP	O
پاروں	PSP	O
براہمناں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
نہ	NEG	O
تاں	PRT	O
ایس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
ویدی	NN	O
رہن	VBI	O
دتا	AUXA	O
نا	NEG	O
ہی	PRT	O
مدھیادیش	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پوری	JJ	O
بولی	NN	O
ایس	PRP	O
وچ	PSP	O
سمان	NN	O
دیتی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
ادارے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
مڈھلا	JJ	O
کم	NN	O
صوبہ	NN	LOC
سرحد	NN	LOC
دے	PSP	O
بندوبستی	JJ	O
علاقیاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
امن	JJ	O
امان	NN	O
بنائی	VBF	O
رکھن	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
پربندھیاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ہتھ	NN	O
ونڈاونا	VBI	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
نفرت	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
بولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سارے	JJ	O
شہر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
گھراں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تے	CC	O
گھراں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
اتے	CC	O
اسمان	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
دوہاں	OD	O
پاسے	NN	O
رنگ	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
رنگ	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پلیز	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
مائنڈ	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
کریں	VBF	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

اس	PRP	O
طرح	PSP	O
کرن	VBI	O
نال	PSP	O
جو	PRR	O
سانوں	PRP	O
اج	NN	O
ملک	NN	O
اندر	NN	O
ڈاکٹراں	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
ہور	Q	O
مہارت	NN	O
رکھن	VBI	O
والیاں	VALA	O
جگہ	NN	O
اپر	NN	O
لگے	VBF	O
ملازماں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کمزور	JJ	O
کارج	NN	O
شیلی	NN	O
کارن	NN	O
لوکاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
بہت	Q	O
نقصان	NN	O
بھگتنا	VBI	O
پے	AUXA	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

سچ	NN	O
کنا	Q	O
سکون	NN	O
ملدا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
پتی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
سیوا	NN	O
کرکے	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

سونیا	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
کروٹ	NN	O
بدلی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اچن	Q	O
چیت	NN	O
مینوں	PRP	O
مجھ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
خیال	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
میرا	PRS	O
ڈر	NN	O
لہہ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تے	SCP	O
میں	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
قسمت	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
سمجھوتہ	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
لیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
ایس	PDM	O
جنم	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
میرے	PRS	O
پاپ	NN	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اوہناں	PDM	O
چر	NN	O
کشٹ	NN	O
بھوگدی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
جناں	Q	O
چر	NN	O
سرج	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
چند	Q	O
آسمان	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
قائم	JJ	O
ہن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

تارا	NN	PER
بولیا	VBF	PER
۔	PU	O

پولیس	NN	O
اک	CD	O
ان	PRE	O
ڈٹھے	JJ	O
دباء	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
ملک	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تیرے	PRS	O
بغیر	PSP	O
میرا	PRS	O
کوئی	PRP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

انسانیت	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
جو	PRR	O
تجربات	NN	O
کیتے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
تہاڈے	PRS	O
ساہمنے	NN	O
نفسیات	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
کتاباں	NN	O
نتھار	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
رکھ	VBF	O
دیندیاں	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

رابعہ	NNP	PER
خان	NN	PER
دیاں	PSP	O
لکھتاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ہک	CD	O
بئی	SC	O
اہم	JJ	O
گالھ	NN	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
چسولی	JJ	O
زبان	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جیندے	PRS	O
وچ	PSP	O
قدم	NN	O
قدم	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ونکو	NN	O
ونک	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
محاورے	NN	O
تے	CC	O
اکھان	NN	O
اوندا	Q	O
چر	NN	O
اربیاوی	JJ	O
ودھا	VBF	O
ڈیندن	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تھاں	NN	O
تھاں	NN	O
افغان	JJ	O
لوگر	NNP	O
ہوٹل	NN	O
افغان	NNP	O
قندھار	NNP	O
ہوٹل	NN	O
افغان	NNP	O
ہرات	NNP	O
ہوٹل	NN	O
کھل	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایں	AUXT	O
پس	NN	O
منظر	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
میدے	NN	O
نزدیک	NN	O
ادب	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
سبھے	JJ	O
صنفاں	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
افسانہ	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
او	PDM	O
صنف	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جیہنے	PRR	O
محض	PRS	O
قصے	NN	O
کہانیاں	NN	O
سٹروالے	NN	O
عام	JJ	O
لوکائی	NN	O
کوں	PSP	O
اتنا	Q	O
معتبر	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
ڈکھا	AUXA	O
یا	CC	O
کہ	SC	O
کہانی	NN	O
ہن	NN	O
شروع	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
انہاں	PRP	O
تے	PSP	O
تھیون	VBI	O
لگی	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
ختم	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
انہائیں	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
۔	PU	O

گاماں	NN	PER
اوہنوں	PRP	PER
نت	NN	O
نماشاں	JJ	O
ویلے	NN	O
پانی	NN	O
دیندا	VBF	O
ہا	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
ویلے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
رکھ	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
ٹردا	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
لگیا	VBF	O
راجیس	NNP	PER
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
ہوائی	JJ	O
اڈے	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
لین	VBI	O
آیا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
آپنے	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
نوں	PSP	O
لندن	NNP	LOC
دے	PSP	O
ائیر	NN	O
پورٹ	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
محسوس	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
اوہدا	PRS	O
تے	CC	O
کر	VBF	O
توں	PRP	O
رہی	AUXP	O
ایں	AUXT	O
میری	PRS	O
مت	NN	O
ماری	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
اوہدیاں	PRS	O
گلاں	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اپنے	APNA	O
بندے	NN	O
تو	PSP	O
نفرت	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

التھا	NN	O
جیوے	VBF	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
کشمیر	NNP	PER
سنگھ	NNP	PER
مارچ	NNP	O
،	PU	O
گل	NN	O
تیہہ	CD	O
ورھے	NN	O
پرانی	JJ	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مرنا	VBI	O
بزدلی	JJ	O
ہووے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

چوہدری	NN	PER
محمد	NNP	PER
اسماعیل	NNP	PER
چیچی	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
کتاب	NN	O
گلستان	NNP	O
رموز	NNP	O
وچ	PSP	O
بیان	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
کارن	NN	O
باغ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اندر	NN	O
جاون	VBI	O
پاروں	PSP	O
جنگلے	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
ٹپ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اندر	NN	O
جانا	VBI	O
پیندا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اپیل	NN	O
خارج	NN	O
ہوگئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بہت	Q	O
ہی	PRT	O
سلیقے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
سجایا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
کمرہ	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

دھیاں	NN	O
ماواں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
پرچھاویں	NN	O
ہوندیاں	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

خورے	RB	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
بچے	NN	O
سویرے	NN	O
سکول	NN	O
جان	VBI	O
توں	PSP	O
پہلاں	NN	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
گھٹ	Q	O
کے	SCK	O
جپھی	NN	O
پائی	VBF	O
وی	PRT	O
ہووے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
مقدمہ	NN	O
ملین	CD	O
ڈالر	NNP	O
دی	PSP	O
خرد	NN	O
بردبارے	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جیہڑا	PRR	O
کوئی	PRP	O
ارب	CD	O
روپے	NN	O
بندے	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
پھیر	RB	O
سہیلیاں	NN	O
دوستاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ملن	VBI	O
لگی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ہاں	INJ	O
کہیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
تاں	PRT	O
گھر	NN	O
وسا	VBF	O
وی	PRT	O
دتا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہناں	PDM	O
تجربیاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
کاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کامیابی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
در	NN	O
ستر	CD	O
فیصد	JJ	O
رہی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پنڈاں	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
دور	NN	O
دراڈے	NN	O
علا	JJ	O
قیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
لوکاں	NN	O
اندر	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
بہت	Q	O
بھاری	JJ	O
تعداد	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
گن	NN	O
موجود	JJ	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
ہن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پیر	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
غصے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایکل	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
سنتاپ	NN	O
بھوگے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
لوکاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
گندے	JJ	O
فقرے	NN	O
سنے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

میرے	PRS	O
گلے	NN	O
چوں	PSP	O
آواز	NN	O
آئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جس	PRR	O
دا	PSP	O
ڈیرا	NN	O
اوہناں	PDM	O
دناں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سیوج	NN	LOC
تے	PSP	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
ک؛د	NN	O
غفورا	NNP	PER
نوری	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
سودے	NN	O
لیان	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پیا	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
پھتے	NN	PER
نوں	PSP	O
فکر	NN	O
پے	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اڑنون	NN	O
۔	PU	O

گاندھی	NNP	PER
تے	CC	PER
تارا	NN	PER
اکٹھے	JJ	PER
بولے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اندروں	NN	O
مانا	VBF	PER
وی	PRT	PER
باہر	NN	O
تھڑے	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
آن	VBI	O
کے	SCK	O
بہہ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

گیتا	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
دو	CD	O
کو	PRT	O
ہفتے	NN	O
کم	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کسے	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
آکے	VBF	O
بچی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
مونہہ	NN	O
تک	PSP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ویکھیا	VBF	O
جیویں	PRR	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
میری	PRS	O
اکلی	JJ	O
دی	PSP	O
غلطی	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
ایس	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
سزا	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
مینوں	PRP	O
ہی	PRT	O
ملنی	VBI	O
چاہی	AUXM	O
دی	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پنشچلی	JJ	O
عورت	NN	O
دوارا	PSP	O
بنایا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
بھوجن	NN	O
جو	PRR	O
وی	PRT	O
انسان	NN	O
کھاندا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
بہت	Q	O
ادھم	NN	O
جاں	CC	O
گھٹیا	JJ	O
بن	VBF	O
جاندا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
اتے	CC	O
اسدے	PRS	O
ست	CD	O
جنماں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ودھیا	JJ	O
کرم	NN	O
نشٹ	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
جاندے	AUXA	O
ہن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
ایتھوں	NN	O
کیہ	RB	O
ملنا	VBI	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مجبور	JJ	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ساڈی	PRS	O
۸۰	CD	O
فیصد	JJ	O
لوک	JJ	O
سوچ	NN	O
بھیڈچال	JJ	O
لکیر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
فقیر	NN	O
والی	VALA	O
ہو	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
چل	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

توں	PRP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
شیرنی	NN	O
بن	VBF	O
شیرنی	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

خورشید	NNP	PER
بیگم	NNP	PER
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
گل	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
بولی	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
کرن	VBI	PER
تے	CC	O
روندی	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
ماں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
پھیر	RB	O
اک	CD	O
واری	NN	O
سر	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
ہتھ	NN	O
پھیریا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اوس	PRP	O
روون	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
ہوکا	NN	O
باہر	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کرن	VBI	PER
دی	PSP	O
واج	NN	O
انج	PRP	O
نکلی	VBF	O
جیویں	PRR	O
کسے	PDM	O
کھوہ	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
آوندی	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
پئی	PRX	O
۔	PU	O

خالدوڈا	NNP	PER
جلسہ	NN	O
کس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
کیتا	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

روی	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
اکھاں	NN	O
کھولیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پچھ	NN	O
پرتیت	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
سلسلہ	NN	O
چلدا	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
پر	SC	O
میری	PRS	O
جیبھ	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
جندرہ	NN	O
لگا	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
۔	PU	O

ہر	JJ	O
محفل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہیر	NNP	PER
وارث	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
پڑھی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
لوکاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
اینی	Q	O
تعداد	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
یاد	NN	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
حیرانی	NN	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بہت	Q	O
لمی	JJ	O
داستان	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
میریاں	PRS	O
زخماں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
سانوں	PRP	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
مسکرایا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جلال	NNP	PER
ہوری	INJ	O
انج	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
میرے	PRS	O
تے	PSP	O
دلے	NN	PER
ہار	NN	O
اک	CD	O
مربعے	NN	O
آلے	VALA	O
نہیں	NEG	O
پنجاں	CD	O
مربعیاں	NN	O
آلے	VALA	O
وڈے	JJ	O
چوہدری	NN	O
باگے	NN	O
آلے	VALA	O
چوہدری	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

چنگا	JJ	O
بندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
اک	CD	O
دن	NN	O
دیہاڑی	NN	O
توڑکے	PSP	O
اوہ	PRP	O
بابو	NN	PER
کرم	NNP	PER
دین	VBI	PER
نال	PSP	O
مچھیاں	NN	O
پکان	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
گوہے	NN	O
بالن	NN	O
اکٹھا	JJ	O
کردا	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
۔	PU	O

پنجاب	NNP	PER
لئی	PSP	O
اج	NN	O
تیک	PSP	O
کس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
تہاڈے	PRS	O
خیال	NN	O
موجب	PSP	O
؟	PU	O

میری	PRS	O
دادی	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
وی	PRT	O
کہ	SC	O
نہ	NEG	O
جاو	VBF	O
ایویں	PRP	O
آپنے	APNA	O
مونہہ	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
ہیگا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
خورے	RB	O
کسراں	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
بولے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ہٹکاںسنسرشپ	NN	O
سارے	JJ	O
وسیباں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہوندیاں	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
اتے	CC	O
اجیہے	PDM	O
ویلے	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
آئے	VBF	O
جد	NN	O
سینمے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
نرا	JJ	O
پراپیگنڈا	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
گیا	AUXA	O
جیویں	PRR	O
نازی	NN	O
جرمنی	NNP	LOC
تے	CC	O
سویت	NNP	LOC
یونین	NN	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کڑیاں	NN	O
منڈیاں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
پیلے	JJ	O
رنگ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کرتے	VBF	O
سوا	VBF	O
لتے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

فیر	RB	O
اک	CD	O
جوان	JJ	O
جہیان	JJ	O
آدمی	NN	O
۔	PU	O

پہلوں	NN	O
تن	CD	O
آنڈے	NN	O
وکھرے	JJ	O
کیتے	VBF	O
فیر	RB	O
اک	CD	O
واپس	NN	O
دھر	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

غفورے	NN	PER
جو	PRR	O
کرناسی	VBF	O
جیرے	NN	PER
نوں	PSP	O
پتاسی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

نوری	NNP	PER
بی	NNP	PER
بی	NNP	PER
سر	NN	O
چکیاتے	VBF	O
دو	CD	O
اوپریاں	JJ	O
چپلیاں	NN	O
نظر	NN	O
آئیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
سمجھ	VBF	O
نہیں	NEG	O
آرہیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
اچانک	RB	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ماں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
رونا	VBI	O
کیوں	RB	O
شروع	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

)	PU	O
تے	CC	O
مقامی	JJ	O
لوک	NN	O
جیہڑی	PRR	O
بولی	NN	O
بولدے	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
اپ	JJ	O
بھرنش	NN	O
(	PU	O
ایس	PRP	O
دیاں	PSP	O
27	CD	O
قسماں	NN	O
،	PU	O
مثلا	JJ	O
کوئی	PDM	O
پت	NN	O
کیہندا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کوئی	PDM	O
پتر	NN	O
)	PU	O
کہلائی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مذہبی	JJ	O
مبلغ	NN	O
پنڈاں	NN	O
تھاواں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
جا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
مناظرے	NN	O
کردے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
اپنیاں	APNA	O
گلاں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
متاثر	JJ	O
کردے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

آہو	INJ	O
یار	NN	O
۔	PU	O

دیوان	NN	ORG
سلمان	NNP	ORG
فائبرز	NN	ORG
دنیا	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
گیارہویں	OD	O
نمبر	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کوٹ	NNP	O
رادھا	NNP	O
کشن	NNP	O
دکھانتمذہبی	JJ	O
جنون	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بھرواں	JJ	O
نمونا	NN	O
پواڑہ	NN	O
امریکہ	NNP	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
فیدے	NN	O
چینیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
خادم	NN	PER
اعلی	JJ	PER
دے	PSP	O
تیرھاں	CD	O
سرکاری	JJ	O
دفتر	NN	O
شاہ	NNP	ORG
حسین	NNP	ORG
کالج	NN	ORG
نوں	PSP	O
ختم	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
کیتا	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
وچارہ	NN	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
گڈ	NNP	O
گورننس	NNP	O
مبارک	NNP	O
وچارہ	NN	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
وچارہ	RB	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
بھٹو	NNP	PER
ازم	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
نعرہ	NN	O
کافی	Q	O
نہیں	NEG	O
امریکی	JJ	LOC
انقلاب	NN	O
سر	NN	O
پرنے	PSP	O
ربڑی	JJ	O
دودھ	NN	O
تے	CC	O
دہی	NNP	O
بھلیاں	PRP	O
والا	VALA	O
صدر	NN	O
امریکی	JJ	LOC
انقلاب	NN	O
سر	NN	O
پرنے	PSP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
آئی	NNP	O
پی	NNP	O
نیں	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
بدمعاش	JJ	O
؟	PU	O

رقیہ	NNP	PER
بیگم	NN	PER
لمی	JJ	O
پے	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

میتھوں	PRP	O
خوشی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
گل	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہو	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
ساہ	NN	O
چڑھ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
میرا	PRS	O
جیویں	PRR	O
کوئی	PDM	O
پہاڑ	NN	O
چڑھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
آئی	VBF	O
ہوواں	AUXA	O
اوس	PDM	O
رات	NN	O
پہلی	OD	O
وار	NN	O
پردیپ	NN	PER
میرے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
ستا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

چنے	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
ایواناں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
زنانیاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
نمائندگی	NN	O
ودھاون	VBI	O
بارے	PSP	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
سیٹاں	NN	O
ودھا	VBF	O
دیون	AUXA	O
نال	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
فرق	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
پیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

انج	PRP	O
بھاویں	RB	O
ادھا	FR	O
محلہ	NN	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
توںددھ	PSP	O
لیندا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
ہن	NN	O
سارے	JJ	O
ایہناں	PDM	O
مجھاں	NN	O
نوںکڈھن	VBI	O
اتے	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
مٹھ	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

رجنی	NNP	O
نوں	PSP	O
چیتے	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
پھیر	RB	O
پتہ	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سماں	NN	O
کیویں	RB	O
اڈ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

جدوں	NN	O
جغرافیائی	JJ	O
حداں	NN	O
مک	VBF	O
جان	AUXA	O
گیئاں	AUXA	O
اودوں	NN	O
سانجھا	JJ	O
کلچر	NN	O
باقی	JJ	O
رہوے	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جد	NN	O
صغراں	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
ہتھوں	NN	O
گلاس	NN	O
ڈگیاتے	VBF	O
اوہ	PRP	O
رڑھدا	VBF	O
گامو	NN	PER
دے	PSP	O
تخت	NN	O
پوش	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ہیٹھوں	NN	O
لنگھدا	VBF	O
رام	NNP	PER
چند	NNP	PER
تماکھو	NN	PER
والے	VALA	PER
دی	PSP	O
ہٹی	NN	O
اگے	NN	O
وگدی	VBF	O
نالی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
جا	VBF	O
ڈگیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
یاداں	NN	O
موت	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
گلیاں	NN	O
چوں	PSP	O
ہو	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
لنگھدیاں	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
حاکم	NN	O
جرنیلاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
پارلیمانی	JJ	O
بالادستی	NN	O
منظور	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
مننی	VBI	O
آں	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
کاں	NN	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
وسیب	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ہک	CD	O
جانی	JJ	O
پہچانی	JJ	O
نشانی	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ہیر	NNP	PER
تے	CC	O
رانجھا	NNP	PER
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
دے	PSP	O
لوکاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اندر	NN	O
وسدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
کیہو	RB	O
جیہی	PRR	O
عجیب	JJ	O
حالت	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

عامرریاض	NNP	PER
پرکجھ	JJ	O
لوکاں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اجیہا	PRP	O
کرن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
کوشش	NN	O
ضرورکیتی	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

سانوں	PRP	O
ساری	JJ	O
دنیا	NN	O
جان	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اسیں	PRP	O
اوہدی	PRS	O
خوشی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
خوش	JJ	O
آں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

قہقہے	NN	O
اجوئے	PSP	PER
رائے	NN	PER
ایہہ	PRP	O
ٹھکواںہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بھا	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ہٹی	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
رش	NN	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
شہباز	NNP	PER
وی	PRT	PER
اوتھے	NN	O
کھلو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

راتی	NN	O
دال	NN	O
سبزی	NN	O
بھیوں	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
رکھ	VBF	O
دیندی	AUXA	O
کسے	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
متھے	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
لگدی	VBF	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

یورپی	JJ	ORG
یونین	NN	ORG
دا	PSP	O
تازہ	JJ	O
اجلاس	NN	O
بے	JJ	O
وطنے	NN	O
ایجنڈے	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
عبائیا	NN	O
لاہون	VBI	O
تے	CC	O
زنانی	NN	O
گرفتار	JJ	O
برطانوی	JJ	PER
وزیراعظم	NN	PER
دا	PSP	O
ایران	NNP	LOC
مخالف	JJ	O
بیان	NN	O
شدید	JJ	O
ردعمل	NN	O
ٹرمپ	NNP	PER
دا	PSP	O
مشیر	NN	O
ماسکو	NNP	O
وچ	PSP	O
؟	PU	O

روی	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
اوس	PRP	O
ول	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
دھیان	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
دتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ویکھو	VBF	O
ناں	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
۔	PU	O

میرا	PRS	O
ککھ	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
رہیا	VBF	O
نہ	NEG	O
میں	PRP	O
اگا	VBF	O
نہہ	NN	O
جوگی	NN	O
رہی	VBF	O
نہ	NEG	O
پچھا	NEG	O
نہہ	NN	O
جوگی	NN	O
۔	PU	O

منوسمریتی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
کیہا	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
کوئی	PDM	O
عورت	NN	O
اپنے	APNA	O
خاوند	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
دھوکھا	NN	O
کردی	VBF	O
ہےدوسرے	AUXT	O
مرد	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
سنبھوگ	NN	O
کردی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
تاں	SC	O
راجے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
حکم	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اس	PDM	O
عورت	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
سر	NN	O
عامکتیاں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
پھڑوا	VBF	O
دیوے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
کہہ	VBF	O
لو	NN	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
دوآں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
جان	VBI	O
تے	PSP	O
بنی	VBF	O
ہوئی	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ناف	NN	O
سے	PSP	O
دومٹھی	NN	O
نیچے	NN	O
کپڑا	NN	O
باندھتے	VBF	O
ہیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اچن	Q	O
چیت	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
سونیا	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
بلھاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
کسے	PDM	O
پنجابی	JJ	O
گیتی	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
سطراں	NN	O
آگئیاں	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
مسکرا	VBF	O
پئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
پتہ	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
تسیں	PRP	O
ہسو	VBF	O
گے	AUXT	O
ایس	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
،	PU	O
پر	SC	O
انج	PRP	O
ای	PRT	O
ہویا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

غلام	NN	PER
فرید	NNP	PER
گزریا	VBF	O
ویلا	NN	O
یاد	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
دوہتھڑ	NN	O
پٹ	VBF	O
اٹھدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
ہن	NN	O
تاں	PRT	O
بھین	NN	O
بختاور	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
چھ	CD	O
کلے	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
نہ	NEG	O
رہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

خورے	RB	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
کیہڑے	PDM	O
ویلے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
دعا	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اجیہے	PDM	O
رنگ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
جھٹ	NN	O
پوری	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تے	SCP	O
جے	SC	O
وس	NN	O
چلدا	VBF	O
تے	SC	O
شائد	RB	O
اوہ	PRP	O
سونے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
سنگل	NN	O
گل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
پا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
چلدا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
حوالے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
چراغ	NN	PER
دین	NNP	PER
جونے	NNP	O
کے	PSP	O
والے	VALA	O
دے	PSP	O
بیان	NN	O
کیتے	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
کجھ	Q	O
اکھان	NN	O
ویکھو	VBF	O
گھراں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
لونی	CD	O
مجلس	NN	O
مندی	JJ	O
مڑ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
پچھو	VBF	O
تون	NN	O
شادیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
وچ	PSP	O
رونا	VBI	O
مندا	JJ	O
غمیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
وچ	PSP	O
گون	NN	O
دکھیاندی	VBF	O
کیہ	RB	O
سار	NN	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
جیہڑے	PRR	O
سکھیں	NN	O
سون	VBI	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

ڈاکٹر	NN	PER
جمیل	NNP	PER
جالبی	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
کلچر	NN	O
بارے	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
وچار	NN	O
ایس	PRP	O
طرح	PSP	O
بیان	NN	O
کیتے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

میرا	PRS	O
دل	NN	O
کرے	VBF	O
پئی	SC	O
تینوں	PRP	O
کھرچ	VBF	O
کھرچ	VBF	O
دیکھا	VBF	O
پئی	SC	O
اصل	NN	O
کیہ	RB	O
اے	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

یاراں	NN	O
بیلیاں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
پچھ	NN	O
گچھ	NN	O
کیتی	VBF	O
کسے	PRP	O
نال	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
رابطہ	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
مینوں	PRP	O
لگدا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
خورے	RB	O
بحیثیت	RB	O
دکھنی	JJ	O
ایشیائی	NN	O
سانوں	PRP	O
تاریخ	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
لگا	VBF	O
وی	PRT	O
کجھ	Q	O
گھٹ	Q	O
ای	PRT	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سیکس	NN	O
تاں	PRT	O
کسے	PRP	O
نال	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
کیتا	VBF	O
جاسکدا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
عشق	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

برانڈرٹھ	NNP	O
دوڈ	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
شاید	RB	O
مسٹر	NN	O
برابڈرتھ	NNP	O
کدی	NN	O
لنگھیا	VBF	O
وی	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اگلے	JJ	O
دن	NN	O
فاطماں	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
ڈھڈ	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
تن	CD	O
سیر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
رسولی	NN	O
نکلی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اک	CD	O
دیہاڑے	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
بڑی	JJ	O
کھیڑے	NN	O
پے	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

شعور	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ارتقاء	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
چیزاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ارتقاء	NN	O
ضروری	JJ	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہدا	PRS	O
پتر	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
میں	PRP	O
کٹھے	NN	O
پڑھدے	VBF	O
ساں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کوئی	PDM	O
نویں	JJ	O
گل	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
ساری	JJ	O
دنیا	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
مرد	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
اپنی	APNA	O
عورت	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
کہندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
توں	PRP	O
مینوں	PRP	O
پسند	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
میں	PRP	O
تاں	PRT	O
گل	NN	O
پیا	VBF	O
ڈھول	NN	O
وجا	VBF	O
رہیاں	AUXP	O
۔	PU	O

انیتا	NNP	PER
روی	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
کسے	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
طریقے	NN	O
ہسا	VBF	O
دینا	AUXA	O
چاہندی	AUXM	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
رو	VBF	O
پئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
پینتڑیاں	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
ہک	CD	O
اچالا	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
میجر	NN	PER
اسحاق	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
ہی	PRT	O
دسی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بندہ	NN	O
بنایا	VBF	O
کنے	Q	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بے	NN	O
غیرت	NN	O
جٹاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
منڈے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ویاہ	NN	O
کروائیں	VBF	O
گے	AUXT	O
بے	NN	O
شرمے	JJ	O
کیوں	RB	O
پیو	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پگ	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
داغ	NN	O
لاون	VBI	O
لگی	AUXA	O
ایں	AUXT	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

انج	PRP	O
پشاور	NNP	LOC
کانپور	NNP	LOC
تے	CC	O
میرٹھ	NNP	LOC
سازش	NN	O
کیس	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
کیمونسٹاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
وکھووکھ	JJ	O
مراکز	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
پتہ	NN	O
دیندے	VBF	O
میرٹھ	JJ	LOC
سازش	NN	O
کیس	NN	O
۱۳۹۱ئ	CD	O
دے	PSP	O
مگروںفیر	NN	O
مرکزی	JJ	O
تنظیم	NN	O
بناون	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
شروع	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
۷۳۹۱ء	FF	O
وچ	PSP	O
جیہڑی	PRD	O
مرکزی	JJ	O
تنظیم	NN	O
بنی	VBF	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
سیکرٹری	NN	O
جنرل	NN	O
پی	NNP	PER
سی	NNP	PER
جوشی	NNP	PER
بنے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
جے	SC	O
مسلمان	JJ	O
مرد	NN	O
ہندو	JJ	O
تہواراں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
آون	VBI	O
وچ	PSP	O
دلچسپی	NN	O
رکھن	VBI	O
تے	CC	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
پہلے	NN	O
ہندو	JJ	O
دھرم	NN	O
قبولنا	VBI	O
پوے	AUXA	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کمانڈر	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
ساتھیاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
مل	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
کراچی	NNP	LOC
دا	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
وڈا	JJ	O
بنک	NN	O
لٹن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
تیاری	NN	O
کیتی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میاں	NN	PER
صاحب	NN	PER
ؒ	NNP	PER
فرماندے	VBF	O
ہن	AUXT	O
ریت	NN	O
وجود	NN	O
تیر	VBF	O
ے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سونا	NN	O
ایویں	PRP	O
نظر	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
آوے	VBF	O
ہنجواں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
گھت	VBF	O
پانی	NN	O
دھوویں	JJ	O
ریت	NN	O
مٹی	NN	O
رڑھ	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
پارہ	NN	O
گھت	VBF	O
محبت	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
گولی	NN	O
ہک	CD	O
بناوے	VBF	O
خاک	NN	O
رلے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
خاک	NN	O
محمدؒ	NNP	O
،	PU	O
سونا	JJ	O
قیمت	NN	O
پاوے	VBF	O
سفرالعشق	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
راہی	NN	O
گھاٹے	JJ	O
وادھے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
سودے	NN	O
بازی	NN	O
اک	CD	O
پاسے	NN	O
سٹ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اپنا	APNA	O
پینڈا	NN	O
ترکھے	VBF	O
پیریں	NN	O
کٹدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ڈر	NN	O
کاہدا	PRS	O
؟	PU	O

یونیورسٹی	NN	ORG
آف	PSP	ORG
مشی	NNP	ORG
گن	NNP	ORG
دے	PSP	O
پولیٹیکل	JJ	PER
سائنسدان	NN	PER
رونالڈ	NNP	PER
دا	PSP	O
آکھنا	VBI	O
ہے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
اک	CD	O
حیرانی	NN	O
والی	VALA	O
کھوج	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اک	CD	O
نرس	NN	O
کول	PSP	O
آ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
کھلوندی	VBF	O
اےبہتیاں	RB	O
مرچاں	NN	O
تاں	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
نیں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

تن	CD	O
صفاں	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
لووجی	AUXA	O
تسیں	PRP	O
اگے	NN	O
آجاوو	VBF	O
بابو	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کراچی	NNP	LOC
والا	VALA	O
پتر	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ویکھیا	VBF	O
پانیاں	NN	O
سبھ	Q	O
رستے	NN	O
روکے	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
کوئی	PRP	O
کیویں	RB	O
آوے	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
رب	NNP	O
دا	PSP	O
قہر	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
ہور	Q	O
دیوو	VBF	O
پپل	NN	ORG
پارٹی	NN	ORG
نو	PSP	O
ں	VBF	O
ووٹاں	NN	O
کوئی	PRP	O
رہ	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
نہیں	NEG	O
گیا	VBF	O
شروع	NN	O
کرو	VBF	O
مولوی	NN	O
صاحب	NN	O
مولوی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
رمال	NN	O
چٹا	JJ	O
اے	VBF	O
بھورے	JJ	O
خانیاں	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
۔	PU	O

اس	PRP	O
طرح	PSP	O
دی	PSP	O
سوچ	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
چاہیدی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

رستے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
جیہڑے	PRD	O
پنڈ	NN	O
آوندے	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
اوہناں	PDM	O
پنڈاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوہ	PRP	O
تبلیغ	NN	O
کردے	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

گرنتھاں	NN	O
کتاباں	NN	O
سمریتیاں	NN	O
،	PU	O
رسماں	NN	O
رواجاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
کنوارے	JJ	O
پن	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
پتی	NN	O
ورتا	NN	O
دھرم	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
النگھن	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
والی	VALA	O
عورتاں	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
اس	PDM	O
جنم	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
ہی	PRT	O
اگلے	JJ	O
جنم	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
اگ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سڑن	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ودھان	NN	O
دسیا	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

بھاویں	RB	O
بچے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
جھکاو	NN	O
صرف	JJ	O
استاد	NN	O
جاں	CC	O
کجھ	Q	O
ہور	Q	O
ہووے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
ایس	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
منکھ	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
ہا	VBF	O
جوں	RB	O
سارے	JJ	O
ترلے	NN	O
تے	CC	O
تراناں	NN	O
مگروں	PSP	O
ایہ	PDM	O
رون	VBI	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
لاہم	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ہر	JJ	O
بندے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
مقسوم	NN	O
کیوں	RB	O
بن	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایسے	PDM	O
رولے	NN	O
گولے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تن	CD	O
چار	CD	O
سال	NN	O
لنگھ	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
کڑی	NN	O
دو	CD	O
بالاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ماں	NN	O
ہوگئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اج	NN	O
ڈیڈھ	FR	O
سو	CD	O
گھر	NN	O
تے	CC	O
دو	CD	O
مسیتاں	NN	O
دووے	JJ	O
مولوی	NN	PER
کلیم	NNP	PER
اللہ	NNP	PER
ہوراں	INJ	O
دی	PSP	O
برکت	NN	O
۔	PU	O

سبھ	Q	O
انھیرے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ساتھی	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
غصے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
آپنی	APNA	O
پتنی	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
نقلاں	NN	O
اتار	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کتا	NN	O
کھوہ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہی	PRT	O
رہندا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
تاں	SC	O
اساں	PRP	O
بوہکیاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
نکلے	VBF	O
پانی	NN	O
نوںپھوکاں	PSP	O
مار	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
پی	VBF	O
لین	AUXA	O
تے	PSP	O
راضی	JJ	O
۔	PU	O

میری	PRS	O
گل	NN	O
من	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اسیں	PDM	O
کتاباں	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
چھپوایا	VBF	O
ں	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

چشم	JJ	O
بدور	NN	O
۔	PU	O

ڈیڈھ	FR	O
دو	CD	O
مہینے	NN	O
پہلاں	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
کراچی	NNP	O
آئی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
میامی	NNP	O
لئی	PSP	O
واپسی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
فلائٹ	NN	O
مہناز	NNP	O
نے	PSP	O
بحرین	NNP	O
توں	PSP	O
پھڑنی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
جنوری	NNP	O
ء	SYM	O
نوں	PSP	O
بحرین	NNP	O
ائر	NN	O
پورٹ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
لاونج	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوہ	PRP	O
چکرا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ایسی	PRP	O
ڈگی	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
مڑ	VBF	O
اٹھ	VBF	O
نہ	NEG	O
سکی	AUXM	O
اللہ	NNP	O
نوں	PSP	O
پیاری	JJ	O
ہوگئی	AUXA	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

پاکستان	NNP	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
جائیداد	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
اصل	JJ	O
قیمت	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
تھاں	NN	O
قیمتاں	NN	O
گھٹ	Q	O
کرکے	PSP	O
وکھائیاں	VBF	O
جاندیاں	AUXA	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

ایک	CD	O
کا	PSP	O
نام	NN	O
اعظم	NNP	PER
ہے	VBF	O
دوسرے	OD	O
اعلی	JJ	PER
وہ	PRP	O
تو	PRT	O
ٹھیک	JJ	O
ہے	VBF	O
مگر	SC	O
یہ	PDM	O
خانہ	NN	O
خراب	JJ	O
باہر	NN	O
نکل	VBF	O
کر	SCK	O
تمہاری	RB	O
مدد	NN	O
کیوں	RB	O
نہیں	NEG	O
کرتے	VBF	O
سمجھا	RB	O
ان	PRP	O
کی	PSP	O
بھی	PRT	O
سوچ	NN	O
مردہ	JJ	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سگریٹاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ڈبی	NN	O
مروڑ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
میز	NN	O
تھلے	NN	O
سٹی	VBF	O
پئی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہ	PDM	O
شیشا	NN	O
اصل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وڈا	JJ	O
سارا	JJ	O
دروازا	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
جس	PRR	O
نوں	PSP	O
ریلنگ	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
کھچ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اک	CD	O
وارڈ	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
دوجی	OD	O
وارڈ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
درمیان	NN	O
جیوں	PRR	O
اک	CD	O
سرحد	NN	O
جہی	PRT	O
کھڑی	VBF	O
کر	VBF	O
دتی	AUXA	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

توں	PRP	O
مینوں	PRP	O
بچان	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
اپنا	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
وی	PRT	O
داء	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
لا	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
تیرے	PRS	O
کول	PSP	O
ہن	NN	O
کجھ	Q	O
نہیں	NEG	O
بچیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جے	SCP	O
شمائلہ	NNP	PER
نال	PSP	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
تاں	SC	O
جیون	NN	O
انج	PRP	O
نہ	NEG	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
،	PU	O
اوہ	PRP	O
میرا	PRS	O
خیال	NN	O
رکھدی	VBF	O
،	PU	O
میرے	PRS	O
کول	PSP	O
جیون	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
بہت	Q	O
وڈا	JJ	O
سہارا	NN	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
رضا	NN	PER
دا	PSP	O
خیال	NN	O
آندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
تاں	PRT	O
ملاں	NN	O
۔	PU	O

پنڈو	JJ	O
ں	PRT	O
اک	CD	O
بندے	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
دسیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
دلت	JJ	O
سماج	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
منڈے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
تعلقات	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
کڑی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
خاندان	NN	O
والیاں	VALA	O
نوں	PSP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
پسند	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

دلاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وسن	VBI	O
والیاں	VALA	O
نوں	PSP	O
کون	PRP	O
مار	VBF	O
سکیا	AUXM	O
ہے	AUXT	O
اج	NN	O
تیک	PSP	O
بھلا	RB	O
۔	PU	O

گیتا	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
فلیٹ	NN	O
کیہہ	RB	O
ملیا	VBF	O
دتے	AUXA	PER
واسطے	PSP	O
آرام	NN	O
گاہ	NN	O
بن	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
تے	PRT	O
مینوں	PRP	O
ایہناں	PDM	O
سوچاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
جرم	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
تھلاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ٹرا	NN	O
ٹرا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
مار	VBF	O
دیندے	AUXA	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

کوئی	PRP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جناب	NN	O
تسیں	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
بھٹی	NNP	O
تے	CC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
بھٹی	NNP	O
نیں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہنوں	PRP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
اصلی	JJ	O
ابے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ناں	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
پتا	NN	O
۔	PU	O

ڈھائی	FR	O
کروڑ	CD	O
یاں	CC	O
ودھ	Q	O
سرمایاکاری	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
والے	VALA	O
واسطے	PSP	O
کسے	PDM	O
قسم	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پچھ	NN	O
گچھ	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
کرنا	VBI	O
کالے	JJ	O
دھن	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
سفید	JJ	O
کرن	VBI	O
تے	CC	O
کرپشن	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
تحفظ	NN	O
دین	VBI	O
والی	VALA	O
گل	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
آکھی	VBF	O
آسکدی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بھل	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
کہ	SC	O
اوس	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
اگ	NN	O
دھکھدی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اسیں	PRP	O
گلاں	NN	O
کردے	VBF	O
کردے	AUXA	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
دروازے	NN	O
اگے	NN	O
پہنچ	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

میری	PRS	O
ووہٹی	NN	O
جیہڑی	PRR	O
سکولے	NN	O
استانی	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
شامیں	NN	O
بالاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ٹیوشناں	NN	O
پڑھا	VBF	O
پڑھا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کمیٹیاں	NN	O
پاپا	NN	O
کجھ	Q	O
پیسے	NN	O
جوڑے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اساں	PRP	O
ایس	PRP	O
نویں	JJ	O
اسردی	VBF	O
سرکاری	JJ	O
سکیم	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوکھے	JJ	O
سوکھے	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
پلاٹ	NN	O
خرید	VBF	O
لیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

پورا	JJ	O
قصہ	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اوہدا	PRS	O
ہس	NN	O
ہس	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
برا	JJ	O
حال	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تائی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بستر	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
وچھیا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
چھت	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
تائے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
برادری	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
گلاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رجھی	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
تے	CC	O
روندی	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

جد	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
سکول	NN	O
جاندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
پہلی	OD	O
واری	NN	O
جس	PRD	O
ویلے	NN	O
کوئی	PDM	O
استاد	NN	O
بلیک	NNP	O
بورڈ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اتے	CC	O
سدھی	JJ	O
لائن	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
سکھاندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
ایہدا	PRS	O
ناں	NN	O
الف	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
بچے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ذہن	NN	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
قبول	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
لیندا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
کیوں	RB	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہنے	PRP	O
اوہ	PDM	O
شکل	NN	O
پہلے	NN	O
کدی	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ویکھی	VBF	O
ہوندی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

کرن	VBI	PER
ای	PRT	O
بوہے	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ملی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اوہنے	PRP	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
دسیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
آپنے	APNA	O
وڈے	JJ	O
منڈے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
گھر	NN	O
گئی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

چانن	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
نیند	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
آوندی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہ	PRP	O
اوس	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
رنگ	NN	O
جو	PRR	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
چڑھیا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پھتے	NNP	PER
حرامدے	NN	PER
دا	PSP	O
گھراڑیاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کارخانا	NN	O
پورے	JJ	O
زور	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
چلدا	VBF	O
پیا	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

خالداحراری	JJ	PER
لیڈراں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
ملدے	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
تسی	PRP	O
؟	PU	O

دریا	NN	O
سکے	AUXM	O
تے	CC	O
وسوں	NN	O
وسیب	NN	O
تے	CC	O
تہذیب	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
رب	NNP	O
راکھا	VBI	O
ہک	CD	O
ہور	Q	O
بابے	NN	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
کیہڑی	PRP	O
کیہڑی	PDM	O
ریت	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ماتم	NN	O
کرئیے	VBF	O
ساڈی	PRS	O
وسوں	NN	O
تے	CC	O
وسیب	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ان	PRE	O
گانجے	NN	O
موتی	NN	O
رل	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
ساڈی	PRS	O
رہتل	NN	O
اپنے	APNA	O
آئین	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
بھلن	VBI	O
نال	PSP	O
جیویں	PRR	O
اجڑ	VBF	O
پجڑ	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

شہری	JJ	O
بابو	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
موسیقار	NN	O
رشید	NNP	PER
عطرے	NNP	PER
تے	CC	O
پتن	NN	LOC
دے	PSP	O
بابا	NN	PER
چشتی	NNP	PER
سن	VBF	O
اینہاں	PDM	O
دونہواں	OD	O
فلماں	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
زنانہ	JJ	O
آوازاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
سارے	JJ	O
گیت	NN	O
زبیدہ	NNP	PER
خانم	NNP	PER
توں	PSP	O
گوائے	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
جدوں	SC	O
کہ	SC	O
دو	CD	O
گانیاں	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
عنایت	NNP	PER
بھٹی	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
آواز	NN	O
شامل	JJ	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

میرے	PRS	O
جنازے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
موڈھا	NN	O
دین	VBI	O
والیاں	VALA	O
وچ	PSP	O
منگل	NNP	PER
چاچا	NN	PER
وی	PRT	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

انکل	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
میں	PRP	O
کدے	NN	O
سوچیا	VBF	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ایداں	PRP	O
دیاں	PSP	O
گلاں	NN	O
بارے	PSP	O
میں	PRP	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

فاقیاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
نوبت	NN	O
آگئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

چودھری	NN	PER
صاحب	NN	PER
نوں	PSP	O
طلاق	NN	O
دے	VBF	O
دیویں	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

جیونی	NN	PER
ساریاں	JJ	O
گلاں	NN	O
سنن	VBI	O
مگروں	PSP	O
اٹھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اندروں	NN	O
بلدا	VBF	O
دیوا	NN	O
چک	VBF	O
لیائی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

دیس	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
وسیلیاں	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
قبضہ	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سرکار	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
کجھ	Q	O
امید	NN	O
ضرور	RB	O
ہے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
معاشی	JJ	O
طور	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
کجھ	Q	O
مدد	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دے	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
بڈھیپا	NN	O
سکون	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
نکل	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

نال	PSP	O
نہ	NEG	O
لے	VBF	O
جاو	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اصلوں	JJ	O
سرمایاکاری	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
تعلق	NN	O
منافع	NN	O
کمان	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جیہڑے	PRR	O
کیری	NNP	PER
ہوراں	INJ	O
ترجمے	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
نظرثانی	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بھا	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
۔	PU	O

جوں	RB	O
جوں	RB	O
رات	NN	O
لنگھی	VBF	O
تیوں	NN	O
تیوں	NN	O
اچیت	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
کس	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
بنھیا	VBF	O
ورھیاں	NN	O
بدھیاں	JJ	O
یاداں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
اٹیچی	NN	O
کیس	NN	O
اچن	PSP	O
چیت	NN	O
اک	CD	O
دم	NN	O
کھل	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
سبھ	Q	O
پرانا	JJ	O
باہر	NN	O
ڈگ	VBF	O
پیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ہاں	INJ	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

تے	SCP	O
اوہ	PRP	O
پھتے	NNP	PER
حرامدے	NN	PER
کولوں	PSP	O
ہور	Q	O
منگوا	VBF	O
لیندا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

مولوی	NN	O
فرزند	NN	O
علی	NNP	O
دیو	NNP	O
بند	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
خطبہ	NN	O
سکھدیاں	VBF	O
سکھیا	NN	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
پہلے	NN	O
اک	CD	O
فقرہ	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
لوو	AUXA	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
دو	CD	O
جا	VBF	O
جوڑو	AUXA	O
پہلے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
جور	NN	O
کھا	VBF	O
ندا	SCK	O
پھیر	RB	O
تیجا	OD	O
چو	NN	O
تھا	VBF	O
پنجویں	OD	O
تے	PSP	O
ضرور	RB	O
کوئی	PRP	O
نہ	NEG	O
کوئی	PRP	O
سبحان	NNP	O
اللہ	NNP	O
کہہ	VBF	O
دیو	AUXA	O
ے	RB	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

عروج	NN	O
تے	CC	O
زوال	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
د	SYM	O
استان	NN	O
انسانی	JJ	O
تاریخ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہمیشہ	RB	O
دہرائی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
رہی	AUXP	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
دہرائی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
رہوہے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

خالہ	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
لون	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
پانی	NN	O
پیتا	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
حالت	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
اسری	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
کمزوری	NN	O
کوئی	PDM	O
تھوڑا	Q	O
سماں	NN	O
پچھے	NN	O
پیدا	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہدے	PRS	O
توں	PSP	O
بچن	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
حفاظتی	JJ	O
ٹیکے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
استعمال	NN	O
مناسب	JJ	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
پرماتما	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
ایڈی	Q	O
چھیتی	JJ	O
اپنے	APNA	O
قانون	NN	O
کیویں	RB	O
بدل	VBF	O
لئے	AUXA	O
؟	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
کہن	VBI	O
لگی	AUXA	O
میرا	PRS	O
آنا	NN	O
نالی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ڈگ	VBF	O
پیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
میں	PRP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
کیہڑا	PRP	O
آنا	VBI	O
؟	PU	O

اوس	PDM	O
ویلے	NN	O
حافظ	NN	PER
غلام	NNP	PER
مرتضی	NNP	PER
وی	PRT	O
حیات	NNP	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اینے	Q	O
نوں	PSP	O
جھاکی	NN	O
مک	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کتھے	NN	O
کیہڑا	PDM	O
کمرا	NN	O
تے	CC	O
کتھے	NN	O
کیہ	RB	O
۔	PU	O

مرد	NN	O
تاں	PRT	O
سارے	JJ	O
کم	NN	O
کاج	NN	O
تے	CC	O
واہی	NN	O
بیجی	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
جا	VBF	O
چکے	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

حقانی	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
منصور	NN	PER
والا	VALA	O
حق	NN	O
ملنا	VBI	O
چاہیدا	AUXM	O
وزیر	NN	O
اعظم	JJ	O
بجلی	NN	O
بحران	NN	O
اک	CD	O
ہور	Q	O
پھڈا	NN	O
گیلانی	NN	PER
بجلی	NN	O
منگی	VBF	O
من	AUXT	O
موہن	NNP	O
دے	PSP	O
دتی	VBF	O
پاکستان	NNP	ORG
سینٹ	NN	ORG
الیکشن	NN	O
جمہوریت	NN	O
پکی	JJ	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
یا	CC	O
ذلیل	JJ	O
پاکستان	NNP	LOC
دوہزار	CD	O
باراں	CD	O
دے	PSP	O
اخیر	NN	O
تیکر	PSP	O
ہندوستان	NNP	LOC
نال	PSP	O
بیوپار	NN	O
نارمل	JJ	O
بلوچستان	NNP	LOC
پاک	NNP	LOC
ایران	NNP	LOC
سانجھ	NN	O
یا	CC	O
گٹھ	NN	O
جوڑ	NN	O
بلوچستان	NNP	LOC
کارڈ	NN	O
پاکستان	NNP	LOC
تے	CC	O
امریکہ	NNP	LOC
دا	PSP	O
بھیڑ	NN	O
یا	CC	O
وارننگ	NN	O
؟	PU	O

اوہدے	PRS	O
بیلی	NN	O
تے	CC	O
کلاس	NN	O
فیلو	NN	O
منوہر	NNP	PER
لال	NNP	PER
مینوں	PRP	O
دسیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اقبال	NNP	PER
اوما	NNP	PER
کشیپ	NNP	PER
کامنی	NNP	PER
کاشل	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
پیار	NN	O
کرے	VBF	O
تے	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
روز	NN	O
سویرے	NN	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
ٹانگے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
پچھے	NN	O
پچھے	NN	O
کنیئرڈ	NN	O
کالج	NN	O
تائیں	PSP	O
جایا	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
آپنی	APNA	O
پنج	CD	O
کو	PRT	O
سال	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پھل	NN	O
ورگی	PRR	O
بچی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
میرے	PRS	O
کول	PSP	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
وچوں	PSP	O
کجھ	Q	O
اکھان	JJ	O
مثلثاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ایس	PRP	O
طرح	PSP	O
بیان	NN	O
کیتے	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تنے	OD	O
حرف	NN	O
قرآن	NNP	O
والے	VALA	O
الف	NN	O
لام	NN	O
تے	CC	O
میم	NN	O
تنے	OD	O
چیزاں	NN	O
کوڑیاں	JJ	O
آہندے	VBF	O
مرچ	JJ	O
تماکو	NN	O
فیم	NN	O
تنے	OD	O
چیزاں	NN	O
مٹھیاں	JJ	O
لگن	VBI	O
لاگی	NN	O
کڑم	NN	O
حکیم	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

پھتا	NNP	PER
اوہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ہسدا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بزی	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
،	PU	O
ٹائم	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ملیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہدے	PRS	O
بلہاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
نمی	NN	O
نمی	Q	O
مسکان	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
گڈی	NN	O
بڑی	JJ	O
تیزی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
استاد	NN	O
بالے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
اوس	PDM	O
ورکشاپ	NN	O
ول	PSP	O
بھجی	VBF	O
جا	AUXA	O
رہی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

سارا	JJ	O
ہی	PRT	O
پنڈ	NN	O
تائے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
یاد	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
ہوندا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
اتے	CC	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
کردے	VBF	O
ہوندے	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
اودھر	NN	O
گیا	VBF	O
ہی	PRT	O
کیوں	RB	O
ساری	JJ	O
عمر	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
پریوار	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ملیا	VBF	O
ایدھر	NN	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
پریوار	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
جی	NN	O
ہن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

امیر	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اپنا	APNA	O
سامان	NN	O
مینوں	PRP	O
چکایا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جدوں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
آدمی	NN	O
باتہذیب	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
آپنے	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
نوں	PSP	O
انسان	NN	O
کہاون	NN	O
لگ	VBF	O
پیا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ساری	JJ	O
رات	NN	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
محلے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
لبھدے	VBF	O
پھر	VBF	O
دے	AUXA	O
رہے	AUXP	O
۔	PU	O

اج	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
انتظامی	JJ	O
لوڑاں	NN	O
پاروں	PSP	O
سنگڑ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
ایس	PRP	O
دیاں	PSP	O
سرحداں	NN	O
اڈواڈ	JJ	O
سمے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وکھو	JJ	O
وکھ	JJ	O
رہیاں	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
یقین	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
واسطے	PSP	O
دو	CD	O
چار	CD	O
گلاں	NN	O
ہور	Q	O
پچھیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

غفورا	NN	PER
میرا	PRS	O
کاری	NN	O
گر	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
میری	PRS	O
کھڈی	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
مینوں	PRP	O
دو	CD	O
آنے	NN	O
فی	PRE	O
جوڑا	NN	O
کھڈی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کرایا	VBF	O
دیندا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

دکاناں	NN	O
والیاں	VALA	O
مہنگے	JJ	O
کپڑے	NN	O
پائے	VBF	O
ہوندے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
ڈھڈ	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
وڈے	JJ	O
وڈے	JJ	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

تیرا	PRS	O
کیہہ	RB	O
دھگڑا	NN	O
لگدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O
؟	PU	O

گھر	NN	O
آکے	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
پھیر	RB	O
پنجابی	JJ	O
لکھت	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
گھول	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

انیتا	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
دیدی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
صاف	JJ	O
شبداں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
کہہ	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
واپس	NN	O
رمیش	NNP	PER
کول	PSP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
جاوے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہدے	PRS	O
اپنے	APNA	O
رکناں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
گنتی	NN	O
اک	CD	O
سو	CD	O
اکہتر	CD	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

وی	PRT	O
کالج	NN	O
جالندھر	NNP	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
ایف	NNP	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
آل	NN	O
دوالے	NN	O
بولن	VBI	O
والیاں	VALA	O
ساریاں	JJ	O
زباناں	NN	O
تے	CC	O
بولیاں	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
ون	JJ	O
سونے	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
نویکلے	JJ	O
اکھر	NN	O
محاورے	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ترکیباں	NN	O
لبھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
سخن	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
دیواراں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ایہو	PRP	O
جیہے	PRR	O
نقش	NN	O
بناندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
جیہڑے	PRR	O
اکھاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
بہوں	Q	O
چنگے	JJ	O
لگدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
دلاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
ول	PSP	O
کھچدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جیتے	PRP	O
رہوے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
بلھے	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
وفات	NN	O
قبر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کتبے	NN	O
موجب	PSP	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
جدوں	SC	O
کہ	SC	O
بہت	Q	O
سارے	JJ	O
لوک	NN	O
ء	SYM	O
وی	PRT	O
کہندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

عشق	NN	O
؟	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
عالمی	JJ	O
قنون	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اندر	NN	O
ہونا	VBI	O
چاہیدا	AUXM	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

شیخ	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
نال	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
کھڑا	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
اوس	PDM	O
حد	NN	O
تک	PSP	O
کوئی	PRP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
گیا	VBF	O
بشیرا	RB	PER
بیٹھا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

چار	CD	O
نکات	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
اتفاق	NN	O
پہلے	OD	O
دن	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
ہوگیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
اکسار	Q	O
جانکاری	NN	O
لوڑیندی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
پیہہ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
چنگی	JJ	O
طرحاں	PSP	O
ملیدہ	NN	O
بنائی	VBF	O
ہوئی	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
ہضم	JJ	O
ہون	VBI	O
والی	VALA	O
۔	PU	O

لمے	JJ	O
کالے	JJ	O
سنگھنے	JJ	O
والاں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
قمیض	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
مگروں	PSP	O
سلا	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
دھون	NN	O
تے	CC	O
قطرے	NN	O
ڈگدے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
شاداں	NNP	PER
دیاں	PSP	O
اکھاں	NN	O
بند	JJ	O
ہون	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پیندیاں	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

باہر	NN	O
نکلو	VBF	O
تسیں	PRP	O
سارے	JJ	O
اک	CD	O
جوان	JJ	O
بندہ	NN	O
بولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کجھ	Q	O
دیہاڑاں	NN	O
مگروں	PSP	O
بسنت	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
رت	NN	O
انج	PRP	O
ای	PRT	O
آئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سردار	NN	PER
نے	PSP	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
مونہہ	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
دوجی	OD	O
واری	NN	O
صابن	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
استرے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
نویں	JJ	O
بلیڈ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ادھا	FR	O
ٹوٹا	NN	O
اڑنگ	VBF	O
دے	AUXA	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
ہس	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
سولہ	CD	O
آنے	NN	O
گل	NN	O
کیتی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
توں	PRP	O
بھائی	NN	O
سراج	NNP	PER
اوہ	PRP	O
میرے	PRS	O
والا	VALA	O
الوروز	NN	O
چپ	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
غلے	NN	O
چوں	PSP	O
پیسے	NN	O
کڈھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
لے	VBF	O
جاندا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
میں	PRP	O
ذرا	JJ	O
جھڑکنا	VBF	O
واں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اوہدی	PRS	O
ماں	NN	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
آکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
میرے	PRS	O
گل	NN	O
پے	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
بھئی	SC	O
ہویا	VBF	O
کیہ	RB	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
واسطے	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
کمائی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
نیں	VBF	O
ناں	NN	O
منڈا	NN	O
کھنڈا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
حالے	NN	O
کیہڑا	PRP	O
ایڈا	Q	O
سیانا	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
توں	PRP	O
ہر	JJ	O
ویلے	NN	O
ایہدے	PRS	O
مگر	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
پیا	VBF	O
رہنا	AUXP	O
ایں	AUXT	O
کوڑھیا	JJ	O
۔	PU	O

حسیبہ	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
ڈاکٹر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
گل	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ترجمہ	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پرانے	JJ	O
ویلے	NN	O
چتاردیاں	VBF	O
رج	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
گپاں	NN	O
وڈھیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بھئیاں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
آپنے	APNA	O
کوٹھے	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
رچھ	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
وی	PRT	O
چڑھایا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

گیتا	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
جوب	NN	O
مل	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
آپسی	JJ	O
تجارتی	JJ	O
مال	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سگوں	SC	O
زباناں	NN	O
،	PU	O
رہتلاں	NN	O
شاعری	NN	O
،	PU	O
موسیقی	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
اک	CD	O
دوجے	OD	O
دے	PSP	O
مذہب	NN	O
تے	CC	O
دوجے	OD	O
خیالاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
سندے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
قبولدے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
ایس	PRP	O
طراں	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
نویں	JJ	O
رہتل	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
موڈھی	NN	O
بنے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جد	NN	O
بندہ	NN	O
زنانی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
روح	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
انج	PRP	O
ہک	CD	O
مک	VBF	O
ہو	VBF	O
جائے	AUXA	O
جے	SC	O
ایہدے	PRS	O
وچ	PSP	O
تعقل	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
عنصر	NN	O
کارفرما	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
افلاطونی	JJ	O
عشق	NN	O
اکھواندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بوٹے	NN	PER
بلشٹر	PSP	PER
ہتھ	NN	O
اچا	JJ	O
کرکے	CC	O
اپنی	APNA	O
پگ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
شملا	NN	O
ٹھیک	JJ	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میرا	PRS	O
ہمیشاں	RB	O
سدھا	JJ	O
ساہواں	NN	O
ایہی	PDM	O
فلسفہ	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

"	PU	O
حکومت	NN	O
الہیہ	NNP	O
انسان	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اندر	NN	O
موجود	JJ	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سرکار	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
ہن	NN	O
تیک	PSP	O
صرف	JJ	O
وعدے	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
کیتے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
مدد	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
دے	PSP	O
ہتھیں	NN	O
کجھ	Q	O
نہیں	NEG	O
آیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مجازی	JJ	O
رنگ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رنگیا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
مجاز	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کرداراں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
پرویا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
قصہ	NN	O
حقیقی	JJ	O
رمزاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
بھریا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پہلے	NN	O
تے	PRT	O
گلو	NN	O
گلیں	NN	O
ورجدا	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
۔	PU	O

آپؒ	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
تاں	PRT	O
سب	Q	O
دا	PSP	O
پیار	NN	O
ملیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

معاشی	JJ	O
چتاونی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
سرخ	JJ	O
اشارے	NN	O
بل	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
نیں	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
ول	PSP	O
توجہ	NN	O
دین	VBI	O
والا	VALA	O
کوئی	PRP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
مسئلہ	NN	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
اے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اسیں	PRP	O
سبھ	Q	O
ایہدے	PRS	O
لئی	PSP	O
حکومت	NN	O
ول	PSP	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
آں	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
جو	PRR	O
دراصل	RB	O
آپ	PRF	O
اک	CD	O
مسئلہ	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کنجری	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
اولاد	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

ہن	NN	O
تسی	PRP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
پوچھو	VBF	O
گے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
ایس	PDM	O
ٹائلٹ	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
قیمت	NN	O
کی	PSP	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
آنا	VBI	O
دیو	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

میرا	PRS	O
جگرا	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
جے	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
میرے	PRS	O
ساہویں	NN	O
میرے	PRS	O
ایس	PDM	O
رقیب	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
سینے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
لائی	VBF	O
بیٹھی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

قدرت	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
بہترین	JJ	O
نعمت	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
نوازیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
ہدایت	NN	O
کیتی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
سارے	JJ	O
معاملے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پن	NN	O
چھان	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
نادیندڑ	JJ	O
افسراں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
جون	NNP	O
تک	PSP	O
ٹیکس	NN	O
گوشوارے	NN	O
جمع	NN	O
کران	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
پابند	NN	O
بنایا	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
دوجی	OD	O
صورت	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
کاری	NN	O
الاونس	NN	O
روک	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اوس	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
مار	NN	O
کٹ	VBF	O
کھاندی	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
پیر	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
دی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

بیٹے	NN	O
تیری	PRS	O
ماں	NN	O
اکلی	JJ	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
سوچاں	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
میں	PRP	O
کیہ	RB	O
کرنا	VBI	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مڑ	RB	O
کوئی	PDM	O
ہور	Q	O
خرابی	NN	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
طلاق	NN	O
ہوگی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

انور	NNP	PER
بیوی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
لے	VBF	O
لے	AUXA	O
گھماندا	VBF	O
رہندا	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
میرے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
سدھے	JJ	O
مونہہ	NN	O
گل	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
روادار	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کونے	NN	O
کونے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ماں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
یاد	NN	O
چھپی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

آکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
رمیش	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
ڈیڈی	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
فون	NN	O
رکھ	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

‫	NNP	O
ہوری	INJ	PER
مودی	NNP	PER
حکومت	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ڈاکو	NN	O
راج	NN	O
آکھدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
اتے	CC	O
انہاں	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
پارٹی	NN	O
ٹی	NNP	ORG
ایم	NNP	ORG
سی	NNP	ORG
اج	NN	O
بنگال	NNP	LOC
ہی	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سگوں	SC	O
اروناچل	NNP	O
پردیش	NNP	O
،	PU	O
‫	NNP	O
مانی	NNP	LOC
پور	NNP	LOC
ہریانہ	NNP	LOC
تے	CC	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
پیر	NN	O
پھیلا	VBF	O
چکی	AUXA	O
جے	PRX	O
۔	PU	O

خواجہ	NNP	O
صاحب	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ویلیاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
بڑا	JJ	O
چر	NN	O
مگروں	PSP	O
تیک	PSP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
سڑک	NN	O
آباد	NN	O
رہی	VBF	O
میرا	PRS	O
مطلب	NN	O
لوکی	NN	O
ایس	PDM	O
سڑک	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
گھراں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رہندے	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
میں	PRP	O
ایتھوں	NN	O
بڑی	JJ	O
وار	NN	O
لنگھیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

چوناں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
اگدوں	NN	O
شیر	NNP	O
بنگال	NNP	O
اے	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
فضل	NNP	PER
الحق	NNP	PER
حسین	NNP	PER
شہید	NNP	PER
سہروردی	NNP	PER
تے	CC	O
مولانا	NN	PER
بھاشانی	NNP	PER
ایہناں	PDM	O
تناں	OD	O
مل	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ایک	CD	O
یونائیٹڈ	NNP	O
فرنٹ	NN	O
جگتو	NNP	ORG
فرنٹ	NN	ORG
بنا	VBF	O
چھڈیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

امن	JJ	O
دیہاڑ	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
؟	PU	O

ہائے	INJ	O
ہائے	INJ	O
بس	RB	O
خان	NN	PER
آصف	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
مگر	PSP	O
ہندوستان	NNP	LOC
ٹر	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
تاں	PRT	O
پچھا	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
چھڈدے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
مصیبت	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تاں	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
پوے	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

دنیادار	JJ	O
بندہ	NN	O
دنیا	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
شیواں	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
مالکی	NN	O
رکھنا	VBI	O
چاہوندا	AUXM	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
چاہندا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
دکھنی	JJ	LOC
ایشیاء	NNP	LOC
توں	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
نوجواناں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ایس	PDM	O
وچاردھارا	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
اسلحہ	NN	O
پوان	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
بھرتی	NN	O
کیتاجاوے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
پتہ	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
کیہ	RB	O
کرنا	VBI	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
ہن	NN	O
تقریبا	FR	O
چوتھائی	FR	O
صدی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
خلا	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
بعد	NN	O
سرائیکی	JJ	O
افسانے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تریمت	NN	O
لکھاری	NN	O
آپڑاں	VBF	O
حصہ	NN	O
رلاون	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
ولدے	JJ	O
سروں	NN	O
کوشش	NN	O
کریندی	VBF	O
پئی	AUXP	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
جانے	VBI	O
پچھانے	JJ	O
فاشسٹ	JJ	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ڈاکٹر	NN	PER
ثمر	NNP	PER
مبارک	NNP	PER
دا	PSP	O
دعوی	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جو	PRR	O
اوہ	PRP	O
کوئلہ	NN	O
باہر	NN	O
کڈھن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
تھاںاوس	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
نوں	PSP	O
زمین	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اندر	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
گیس	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
دین	AUXA	O
گے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
ایس	PDM	O
گیس	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
بجلی	NN	O
پیدا	NN	O
ہووے	VBF	O
گی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اک	CD	O
دن	NN	O
جس	PRD	O
ویلے	NN	O
حافظ	NN	PER
صاحبؒ	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
میاں	NNP	PER
صاحب	NN	PER
نوں	PSP	O
یوسف	NNP	O
زلیخا	NNP	O
سناون	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
فرمائش	NN	O
کیتی	VBF	O
تاں	SC	O
آپؒ	PRP	O
آکھن	VBI	O
لگے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

جیہڑا	PRR	O
علم	NN	O
شعور	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
بلوغت	NN	O
دیندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
شعور	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
جمودی	JJ	O
کیفیت	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
دور	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
جیہڑا	PRD	O
شعور	NN	O
علم	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
جمود	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
دور	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
اصل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوہو	PRP	O
ای	PRT	O
شعور	NN	O
تے	CC	O
اوہو	PRP	O
ای	PRT	O
علم	NN	O
اکھوان	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
حق	NN	O
رکھدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

زندگی	NN	O
آرام	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
چل	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کتھے	NN	O
کتھے	NN	O
ماڑی	JJ	O
موٹی	JJ	O
ٹیں	NN	O
پٹاس	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بورڈ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
وڈے	JJ	O
ڈائریکٹر	NN	O
مصباح	NNP	PER
الدین	NNP	PER
فرید	NNP	PER
ہوراں	INJ	O
سارا	JJ	O
ملبہ	NN	O
شہر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
بے	JJ	O
ہنگم	JJ	O
ترقیاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
پاکے	VBF	O
رانجھا	NNP	O
راضی	JJ	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہناں	PRP	O
دیاں	PSP	O
نسلاں	NN	O
ہڑپے	NNP	LOC
نال	PSP	O
تعلق	NN	O
رکھدیاں	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

میری	PRS	O
چنی	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
ریشمی	JJ	O
تنداں	NN	O
وے	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
گھٹ	Q	O
گھٹ	Q	O
دینی	VBI	O
آں	AUXT	O
گنڈھاں	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

پاکستان	NNP	LOC
قومی	JJ	LOC
اسمبلی	NN	LOC
نے	PSP	O
کالا	JJ	O
دھن	NN	O
چٹا	JJ	O
کرن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
قانون	NN	O
منظور	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
لیا	AUXA	O
ایگزٹ	NNP	O
کنٹرول	NN	O
لسٹ	NN	O
جمیل	NNP	PER
احمد	NNP	PER
پال	NNP	O
ایف	NNP	ORG
بی	NNP	ORG
آر	NNP	ORG
نے	PSP	O
ارب	CD	O
رپئے	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
ودھ	Q	O
واجبات	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
وصولی	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
ٹیکس	NN	O
چوراں	NN	O
تے	CC	O
نادیہندڑاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ناں	NN	O
ایگزٹ	JJ	O
کنٹرول	NN	O
لسٹ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
شامل	JJ	O
کروان	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
غور	NN	O
شروع	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
نان	NN	O
فائلرز	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کمپیوٹرائزڈ	JJ	O
قومی	JJ	O
شناختی	NN	O
کارڈ	NN	O
بلاک	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
تجویز	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہو	PDM	O
بھرا	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
۔	PU	O

اج	NN	O
ورھیاں	NN	O
بعد	NN	O
مشرقی	JJ	O
بنگال	NNP	O
دے	PSP	O
سیاسی	JJ	O
سوجھوان	NN	O
کارکن	NN	O
کیہہ	RB	O
سوچ	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
کس	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
وچار	NN	O
وٹاندارا	VBF	O
کر	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
نیں	AUXT	O
کمال	NNP	O
لوہانی	NNP	O
ہوراں	INJ	O
دی	PSP	O
زبانی	NN	O
سنو	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
توں	PRP	O
لگدا	VBF	O
کشمیری	NN	O
جاں	CC	O
پٹھان	NN	O
ایں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مسعود	NNP	PER
واپس	NN	O
ٹرن	VBI	O
لگیا	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
کرن	VBI	PER
نے	PSP	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
زبردستی	NN	O
اندر	NN	O
بٹھا	VBF	O
لیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

پنجابی	JJ	O
بول	NN	O
چال	NN	O
رہن	NN	O
سہن	JJ	O
تعلیم	NN	O
تہذیب	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ثقافتی	JJ	O
عمل	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ہور	Q	O
کماں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ایہناں	PDM	O
سنجیدگی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
دھیان	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
دتا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
کسے	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
پنجابی	JJ	O
پن	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ثبوت	NN	O
دتا	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تازہ	JJ	O
کھڑے	VBF	O
گلاب	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
پھل	NN	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
بچیاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
یاد	NN	O
دلا	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
کسے	PDM	O
شے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
لوء	JJ	O
دل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
بال	VBF	O
لوو	AUXA	O
چر	NN	O
نکل	VBF	O
جاندا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

لال	JJ	O
دارھی	NN	O
تے	CC	O
تیرے	PRS	O
پچھے	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
کھڑا	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جویں	PRR	O
ای	PRT	O
اسیں	PRP	O
مال	NNP	O
روڈ	NN	O
پار	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
میکلوڈ	NNP	LOC
روڈ‫	NNP	LOC
راہیں	PSP	O
یاں	CC	O
ایبٹ	NNP	O
روڈ	NN	O
چیرنگ	NNP	O
کراس	NNP	O
راہیں	PSP	O
اپڑنے	VBI	O
ساں	AUXT	O
،	PU	O
اوڈین	NNP	O
سینما	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
،	PU	O
سارے	JJ	O
سینمے	NN	O
،	PU	O
رجنٹ	NNP	O
،	PU	O
رٹز	NNP	O
،	PU	O
‫	NNP	O
پیلس	NNP	O
،	PU	O
رتن	NNP	O
،	PU	O
صنوبر	NNP	O
،	PU	O
نشاط	NNP	O
تے	CC	O
کپیٹل	NNP	O
،	PU	O
بولی	NN	O
وڈ	NNP	O
تے	CC	O
لولی	NNP	O
وڈ	NNP	O
دیاں	PSP	O
فلماں	NN	O
وکھایاں	VBF	O
جاندیاں	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

صغری	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
جواب	NN	O
دتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کسے	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
قلم	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
چنج	NN	O
توڑ	VBF	O
دیندا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

آکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اوس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
میریاں	PRS	O
زلفاں	NN	O
کھول	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
میرے	PRS	O
گل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
پا	VBF	O
دتیاں	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ہسپتال	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
میرے	PRS	O
ڈاکٹر	NN	O
مینوں	PRP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
تیرا	PRS	O
یڈیٹر	NN	O
گرفتار	JJ	O
ہوگیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
میں	PRP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
اچھاکہن	VBI	O
لگا	AUXA	O
توں	PSP	O
حیران	JJ	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہویا	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

اوتھوں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
بالاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
کئی	Q	O
جماندرو	JJ	O
بیماریاں	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
جیہڑیاںدوئیاں	Q	O
بالاں	NN	O
نوںلگن	PSP	O
دا	PSP	O
ڈر	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
توں	PRP	O
اج	NN	O
مڑ	VBF	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

تے	SCP	O
میرا	PRS	O
نکاح	NN	O
چودھری	NN	PER
صاحب	NN	PER
نال	PSP	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

دو	CD	O
چوں	PSP	O
دناں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
مرکھپ	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
گا	AUXT	O
وچارا	JJ	O
۔	PU	O

ووہٹی	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
رات	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
بجے	NN	O
ہوئے	VBF	O
سالن	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
پراٹھا	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
دتا	VBF	O
ہووے	AUXA	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

وارث	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
مڈھلی	JJ	O
تعلیم	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
بھاویں	RB	O
اوسے	PDM	O
مدرسے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
جتھے	NN	O
بلھے	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
پڑھیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
دوواں	OD	O
دے	PSP	O
فکری	JJ	O
رجحان	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
زمین	NN	O
اسمان	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
فرق	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ابو	NN	O
مینوں	PRP	O
رخصت	JJ	O
کرن	VBI	O
ویلے	NN	O
زاروقطار	PSP	O
رویا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
میریاں	PRS	O
اکھاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہنجو	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سرائیکی	JJ	O
زبان	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ادب	NN	O
جنوبی	JJ	LOC
ایشیاء	NNP	LOC
دے	PSP	O
لسانی	JJ	O
ادبی	JJ	O
مطالعے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پرکار	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
مرکزی	JJ	O
نقطہ	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

دوہاں	OD	O
دے	PSP	O
ویاہاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
سال	NN	O
بھر	VBF	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ڈھول	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
تھاپ	NN	O
ابھری	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
مٹی	NN	O
آں	VBF	O
دھرتی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
مہک	NN	O
اداس	JJ	O
چڑیاں	NN	O
دازخمی	VBF	O
گون	NN	O
اجڑیاں	JJ	O
باگاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
بونٹلی	CD	O
کوئل	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کوک	VBF	O
سکے	AUXM	O
دریاواں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ہوک	NN	O
تے	CC	O
سمے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
چیک	NN	O
قلبوت	JJ	O
مٹی	NN	O
پیڑاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بھار	NN	O
تے	CC	O
رب	NNP	O
رب	NNP	O
ای	PRT	O
رب	NNP	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
کد	NN	O
مک	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
ایہنوں	PRP	O
کس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
استعمال	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کوئی	PDM	O
گورا	JJ	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

ر	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

اوہنوں	PRP	O
بھٹھ	NN	O
جنا	Q	O
تاپ	NN	O
چڑھیا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جی	INJ	O
ہاں	INJ	O
پہلے	NN	O
اوپرا	JJ	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سی	VBF	O
ہن	NN	O
ہوگیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
کیوں	RB	O
جے	SC	O
اک	CD	O
اہم	JJ	O
تاریخی	JJ	O
فکر	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
کوئی	PRP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ٹپ	VBF	O
سکدا	AUXM	O
پرانہہ	NN	O
کھلوتا	VBF	O
رہ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
ایدھر	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
آ	VBF	O
سکدا	AUXM	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
حال	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ماضی	NN	O
قریب	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اوہدا	PRS	O
کوئی	PDM	O
کردار	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
فیر	RB	O
اوہ	PRP	O
کیوں	RB	O
زبانی	JJ	O
تسلسل	NN	O
توڑ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
مستقبل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
آرلے	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بھا	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
نے	PSP	O
شہتیراں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
اگ	NN	O
اتے	PSP	O
سیکدیاں	VBF	O
ہوئے	AUXA	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جنگلی	JJ	O
جانور	NN	O
،	PU	O
اک	CD	O
دوجے	OD	O
نوں	PSP	O
ماردے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
کھان	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

چنانچہ	SCP	O
زبان	NN	O
آلات	NN	O
واوزار	JJ	O
پیداوار	NN	O
کے	PSP	O
طریقے	NN	O
اور	CC	O
سماجی	JJ	O
رشتے	NN	O
رہن	VBI	O
سہن	NN	O
فنون	NN	O
لطیفہ	JJ	O
علم	NN	O
وادب	JJ	O
فلسفہ	NN	O
و	CC	O
حکمت	NN	O
عقائد	NN	O
و	CC	O
افسوں	NN	O
اخلاق	NN	O
و	CC	O
عادات	NN	O
رسوم	NN	O
و	CC	O
روایات	NN	O
عشق	NN	O
ومحبت	NN	O
کے	SCK	O
سلوک	NN	O
اورخاندانی	JJ	O
تعلقات	NN	O
و	CC	O
غیرہ	JJ	O
تہذیب	NN	O
کے	PSP	O
مختلف	JJ	O
مظاہرہیں	NN	O
۔	PU	O

کیہ	RB	O
تسیں	PRP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
آپس	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
صلاح	NN	O
مشورہ	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
کردے	VBF	O
ہو	AUXT	O
؟	PU	O

ساڈے	PRS	O
کول	PSP	O
ایس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
سچ	NN	O
یاں	CC	O
جھوٹھ	NN	O
ثابت	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
دے	PSP	O
وسیلے	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہین	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PRP	O
توں	PSP	O
پہلاں	NN	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PDM	O
نمبر	NN	O
ڈائل	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
رب	NNP	O
سببی	PSP	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
اوہدی	PRS	O
ای	PRT	O
کال	NN	O
آگئی	VBF	O
جیہدی	PRS	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
اڈیک	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
ہیلو	INJ	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
سب	Q	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
سمجھا	VBF	O
سمجھا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
تھک	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
پر	SC	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
ہنجو	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
مک	VBF	O
رہے	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ہن	NN	O
میرے	PRS	O
سجناں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
اوہ	PDM	O
گھر	NN	O
جیہناں	PRR	O
دا	PSP	O
میں	PRP	O
ہار	NN	O
سنگھار	NN	O
تے	CC	O
زینت	NN	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
ساں	AUXT	O
اوہناں	PDM	O
گھراں	NN	O
کاں	NN	O
مار	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
تے	CC	O
آپدی	APNA	O
چھت	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ٹنگ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
ہوکرا	NN	O
دے	VBF	O
چھڈیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
گھر	NN	O
کاں	NN	O
مار	VBF	O
ہین	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
ہن	NN	O
کوئی	PDM	O
کاں	NN	O
پرانی	JJ	O
یاری	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
ہڑک	NN	O
لے	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ایدھر	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
تاں	SC	O
اوہدا	PRS	O
وی	PRT	O
ایہو	PDM	O
حشر	NN	O
ہووے	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

تینوں	PRP	O
کھان	VBI	O
لگا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
۔	PU	O

گیتا	NN	PER
چپ	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
موٹی	JJ	O
عقل	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ساں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میریاں	PRS	O
ہمدرد	NN	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PDM	O
اکھاں	NN	O
اپر	NN	O
چڑھا	VBF	O
لئیاں	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
زور	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کھڑکھڑا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ہس	VBF	O
پئی	AUXA	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

کنا	Q	O
گھٹ	Q	O
بولدا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
فیر	RB	O
پچھیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مولبی	NN	O
رات	NN	O
باگے	NN	O
آلی	VALA	O
کوٹھی	NN	O
رہوے	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

زی	NNP	ORG
ٹی	NNP	ORG
وی	NNP	ORG
دا	PSP	O
چیئرمین	NN	O
بارہویں	OD	O
وچ	PSP	O
پڑھائی	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
بھگوڑا	NN	O
ہوگیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

راء	NNP	PER
بیگ	NNP	PER
ڈھڈیوں	NN	LOC
دا	PSP	O
سردار	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
چھوہر	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ازلی	NN	O
لگی	VBF	O
نوں	PSP	O
تروڑن	VBI	O
تے	PSP	O
مینوں	PRP	O
پوجھن	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
سٹن	VBI	O
تے	PSP	O
ذرا	JJ	O
وی	PRT	O
ترس	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
آیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مینوں	PRP	O
چانچک	RB	O
یاد	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
جو	PRR	O
میں	PRP	O
سلطان	NNP	O
باہو	NNP	O
دا	PSP	O
یہہ	CD	O
شعرساری	JJ	O
عمر	NN	O
سنیا	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
کدی	NN	O
ایس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
چنگی	JJ	O
طرحاں	PSP	O
سمجھیا	VBF	O
یا	CC	O
سلاہیا	VBF	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

میرا	PRS	O
پتی	NN	O
کسے	PDM	O
ویہہ	CD	O
بائی	CD	O
سال	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کڑی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
تریا	VBF	O
آرہیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پاکستانی	JJ	O
اہلکار	NN	O
ودھیر	Q	O
میرے	PRS	O
توں	PSP	O
وطن	NN	O
خاندان	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
گلاں	NN	O
پچھدے	VBF	O
سوال	NN	O
جواب	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
سلسلہ	NN	O
چلدا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
تینوں	PRP	O
کیویں	RB	O
سمجھاواں	VBF	O
نیتو	NNP	PER
تیرے	PRS	O
سارے	JJ	O
بھین	NN	O
بھرا	NN	O
آپنے	APNA	O
گھراں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سیٹ	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

گیتا	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
پچھیا	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
تیری	PRS	O
اوقات	NN	O
ویکھدا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
بازارو	JJ	O
عورت	NN	O
ویکھدا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
توں	PRP	O
کتھوں	NN	O
تک	PSP	O
گردی	NN	O
ہیں	VBF	O
تیرے	PRS	O
ورگیاں	PRR	O
چھتی	CD	O
سو	CD	O
تریٹھ	CD	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

آپؒ	NNP	O
فرماندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
دنیا	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
نہ	NEG	O
گئی	VBF	O
کسے	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
ٹر	VBF	O
ٹر	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
اکلے	JJ	O
اوہو	PRP	O
بھلے	JJ	O
جہناں	PRR	O
چھنڈ	VBF	O
رکھے	VBF	O
اس	PRP	O
دھوڑوں	PSP	O
ہتھ	NN	O
پلے	VBF	O
دانشمنداں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
ناہیں	NEG	O
دنیا	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
دل	NN	O
لانا	VBI	O
اس	PRP	O
بہٹی	PSP	O
لکھ	CD	O
خاوند	NN	O
کیتے	VBF	O
جو	PRR	O
کیتا	VBF	O
سو	CD	O
کھانا	NN	O
جس	PRR	O
چھڈی	VBF	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
بچے	NN	O
کھانی	VBI	O
سویو	NN	O
سگھڑ	JJ	O
سیانا	JJ	O
ایسی	PRP	O
ڈائن	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
محمدؒ	NNP	PER
کاہنوں	RB	O
عقد	NN	O
نبھانا	VBI	O
نت	NN	O
نویں	JJ	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
بن	VBF	O
بن	VBF	O
بہندی	VBF	O
بڈھی	JJ	O
مول	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
دسدی	VBF	O
ہر	JJ	O
اک	CD	O
سنگ	NN	O
کریندی	VBF	O
گوشے	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
اکی	CD	O
پر	PSP	O
وسدی	VBF	O
سوئیو	Q	O
نیونہہ	NN	O
لگاندا	VBF	O
اس	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
شامت	NN	O
آئی	VBF	O
جس	PRR	O
دی	PSP	O
ہر	JJ	O
بھرتے	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بھرتا	NN	O
کیتوس	VBF	O
بنی	NN	O
محمد	NNP	PER
کس	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
مکدی	JJ	O
گل	NN	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
ہے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
آپؒ	PRP	O
نکی	JJ	O
عمرے	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
دنیا	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
حقیقت	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
چنگی	JJ	O
طراں	PSP	O
جانو	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
چکے	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

رب	NNP	O
توں	PSP	O
ڈر	NN	O
کالی	JJ	O
چدر	JJ	O
ہیتھ	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
رکھ	VBF	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
و	CC	O
تھا	VBF	O
ں	PU	O
وچ	PSP	O
سیمنٹ	NN	O
بھردے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
وچارے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
تاں	PRT	O
بالکل	RB	O
وی	PRT	O
پتا	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
کہ	SC	O
جے	SC	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
کسے	PDM	O
امیر	JJ	O
ملک	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کتی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
پیٹوں	NN	O
جمیا	VBF	O
ہوندا	AUXA	O
تاں	SC	O
کسے	PDM	O
گورے	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
ایہنوں	PRP	O
بسکٹ	NN	O
کھواونے	VBI	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

گول	JJ	O
گھم	VBF	O
گھیر	VBF	O
پوڑیاں	NN	O
پرانیاں	JJ	O
ویلیاں	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
تے	CC	O
جد	NN	O
تسیں	PRP	O
پوڑیاں	NN	O
چڑھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اتے	CC	O
اپڑو	VBF	O
اک	CD	O
لمابرانڈا	NN	O
تے	CC	O
دوجے	OD	O
ہتھ	NN	O
کمریاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پال	NN	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
مڑ	VBF	O
ایس	PRP	O
ساڑے	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
ریلوے	NN	O
سٹیشن	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ورتن	VBI	O
جوگ	PSP	O
بناگیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جدوں	NN	O
اسیں	PRP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
دہی	NN	O
تے	CC	O
اپنے	APNA	O
نفسی	JJ	O
گھنڈیاں	NN	O
تے	CC	O
وا	NN	O
ورولیاں	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
کیڑیاں	NN	O
تہاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
عشق	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
اگ	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ساڑ	VBF	O
دینے	AUXA	O
ہاں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اک	CD	O
دن	NN	O
اینویں	PRP	O
توں	PSP	O
گلاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
دسیاں	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
ویلا	NN	O
اینا	Q	O
بدل	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
تینوں	PRP	O
جاپدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
جیڑے	PRD	O
نوٹس	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
کتاب	NN	O
لکھن	VBI	O
بارے	PSP	O
لئے	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
پرانے	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
ہن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جدوں	NN	O
ہر	JJ	O
پاسے	NN	O
ناامید	NN	O
ویکھی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کمانڈر	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
پگ	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
شلڈن	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
پیرا	JJ	O
ں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رکھدیاں	VBF	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
کجھ	Q	O
وی	PRT	O
کر	VBF	O
او	PRP	O
اوہدی	PRS	O
جان	NN	O
بچا	VBF	O
لیوے	VBF	O
ڈاکٹر	NN	PER
شلڈن	NNP	PER
نے	PSP	O
بڑی	JJ	O
سوچ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
بعد	NN	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
اک	CD	O
طریقہ	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جیدے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
اوہدی	PRS	O
جان	NN	O
بچ	VBF	O
سکدی	AUXM	O
ای	PRT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
تے	PRT	O
مینوں	PRP	O
جیل	NN	O
چوں	PSP	O
باہر	NN	O
آکے	VBF	O
پتہ	NN	O
لگنا	VBI	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
دنیا	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
رنگ	NN	O
بھنگ	NN	O
تے	CC	O
چال	NN	O
کنی	Q	O
بدل	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
کالج	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ہوسٹل	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رہندے	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
ورتدا	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
تے	CC	O
اخیر	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
بازارو	JJ	O
عورت	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ٹھپہ	NN	O
اوس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
متھے	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
لگا	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
درخواست	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
بڑی	JJ	O
اوکھی	JJ	O
اردو	NN	O
فارسی	NNP	O
وچ	PSP	O
لکھیا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
عور	NN	O
ت	NN	O
مسمات	NNP	O
نوری	NNP	PER
فاحشہ	NNP	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سٹا	NN	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
نکلدا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
اساڈے	PRS	O
چوں	PSP	O
چوکھے	Q	O
بال	NN	O
تاں	PRT	O
ایتھوں	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
پڑھائی	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
نابر	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
جاندے	AUXA	O
ہن	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
باقی	JJ	O
اکھاں	NN	O
نوٹ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اجیہارٹا	RB	O
لاوندے	VBF	O
ہن	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
سمجھ	NN	O
ناں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
شے	NN	O
لبھیاں	VBF	O
نہیں	NEG	O
لبھدی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

صرف	JJ	O
تیری	PRS	O
۔	PU	O

اینج	PDM	O
شکاری	NN	O
آپوں	PRF	O
جنگلی	NN	O
حیات	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
بچاون	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
فنڈ	NN	O
کررہے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تاں	SC	O
اساں	PRP	O
نرا	JJ	O
پاکستانی	JJ	LOC
میڈیا	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
کیوں	RB	O
پھنڈیے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

مذہبی	JJ	O
ٹھیکیدار	NN	O
؟	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
گل	NN	O
تاں	PRT	O
ٹھیک	JJ	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PDM	O
جگ	NN	O
جگ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کمی	NN	O
۔	PU	O

بلھے	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
اپنے	APNA	O
مرشد	NN	O
راہیں	PSP	O
قادری	NNP	O
تے	CC	O
دادا	NN	O
مرشد	NN	O
پاروں	PSP	O
شطاری	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

خالہ	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
حالت	NN	O
وگڑدی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
بہت	Q	O
سارے	JJ	O
راہیاں	NN	O
چوں	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
چٹی	JJ	O
چادر	NN	O
تے	CC	O
چٹی	JJ	O
داڑھی	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
بزرگ	NN	O
بولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہدا	PRS	O
فائدہ	NN	O
ملک	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
پہنچے	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
کسے	PDM	O
اک	CD	O
کمپنی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
حکومت	NN	O
ولوں	PSP	O
نوازنا	VBI	O
یاں	CC	O
جذباتی	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اکھاں	NN	O
بند	JJ	O
کر	VBF	O
لین	AUXA	O
نال	PSP	O
فائدہ	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
سگوں	SC	O
نقصان	NN	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
ملکی	JJ	O
معیشت	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
مقابلے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
فضا	NN	O
مک	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
جیہڑی	PRR	O
لبرل	JJ	O
معاشی	JJ	O
پالیسی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
نفی	NN	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ایہدے	PRS	O
لئی	PSP	O
سٹیٹ	NNP	O
بینک	NNP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
توجہ	NN	O
نجی	JJ	O
بچتاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ورتوں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
لیاون	VBI	O
ول	PSP	O
مبذول	NN	O
کرے	VBF	O
تے	SC	O
بچیاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
مثبت	JJ	O
شرح	NN	O
منافع	NN	O
دین	VBI	O
والے	VALA	O
فعال	NN	O
بینکنگ	NN	O
نظام	NN	O
راہیں	PSP	O
نجی	JJ	O
سرمایہ	NN	O
کاری	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
فروغ	NN	O
دتا	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
دوستاں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
کتاب	NN	O
لکھن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
مشورہ	NN	O
دتااے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
نالو	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ڈاکٹر	NN	PER
فاروق	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
وچار	NN	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
نویں	JJ	O
منڈیاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
کیہ	RB	O
جانکاری	NN	O
۔	PU	O

کیوں	RB	O
توں	PRP	O
نواب	NN	O
لگا	VBF	O
ایں	AUXT	O
ایتھے	NN	O
بئی	VBF	O
گھر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
مالک	NN	O
کم	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
تے	CC	O
توں	PRP	O
باہر	NN	O
مزے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
بنٹے	NN	O
کھیڈدا	VBF	O
پھریں	AUXT	O
؟	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
تے	CC	O
بائو	NN	PER
ہردیال	NNP	PER
جین	NNP	LOC
مندر	NN	LOC
کول	PSP	O
اکٹھے	NN	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
گرائونڈ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اپڑدے	VBF	O
جتھے	NN	O
پروفیسر	NN	O
صاحب	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
ساڈی	PRS	O
اڈیک	NN	O
ہووے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بھا	NN	PER
کالا	JJ	PER
گوہ	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ویہندیاں	VBF	O
بولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اجوئے	NN	PER
رائے	NN	PER
جواہر	NNP	PER
لعل	NNP	PER
نہرو	NNP	PER
۔	PU	O

جد	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
غفورے	NNP	PER
نوری	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
گھر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
روٹ	NN	O
لائی	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
اوہ	PRP	O
ہر	JJ	O
کسے	PRP	O
نال	PSP	O
اچیچا	JJ	O
سلام	NN	O
دعا	NN	O
لیندا	VBF	O
گل	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
نیویاں	JJ	O
ہوکے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سورج	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
گرہن	NN	O
لگ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مرزا	NNP	PER
حنیف	NNP	PER
فلم	NN	O
سٹوری	NN	O
رائٹر	NNP	O
مختار	NNP	PER
گیلانی	NN	PER
تے	CC	O
میوزک	NN	O
سنٹر	NN	O
والا	VALA	O
سلیم	NNP	PER
رنگو	NNP	PER
وی	PRT	O
ایتھے	NN	O
بیہندے	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جاندے	VBF	O
جاندے	VBF	O
فیر	RB	O
پچھیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
تے	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
بولے	VBF	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
پنڈ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ایہو	PRP	O
جیہا	PRR	O
پہلا	OD	O
واقعہ	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
ایس	PRP	O
توں	PSP	O
اڈ	JJ	O
اسیں	PRP	O
کجھ	Q	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ویکھیا	VBF	O
نہ	NEG	O
کجھ	Q	O
سنیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
میریاں	PRS	O
اکھاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ویکھدا	VBF	O
ہویا	AUXA	O
بولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ساڈے	PRS	O
کلچر	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تو	CC	O
ہمات	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
اچیچ	NN	O
دتی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مسعود	NNP	PER
وی	PRT	O
اگوں	NN	O
ہس	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ٹر	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
اخیر	NN	O
اک	CD	O
تنگ	JJ	O
جیہی	PRT	O
گلی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
باہر	NN	O
رکیا	VBF	O
اوتھے	NN	O
کندھ	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
لگے	VBF	O
بجلی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
میٹراں	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
بل	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
لکھے	VBF	O
میٹر	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
نمبر	NN	O
رلایا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

تسیں	PRP	O
ویکھو	VBF	O
ادھی	FR	O
ادھی	FR	O
گوٹ	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
اگانہہ	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
گئیاں	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اجے	NN	O
تیکر	PSP	O
میل	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پنج	CD	O
ست	CD	O
جیہڑیاں	PRD	O
گلاں	NN	O
سکھائیاں	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
سارا	JJ	O
دن	NN	O
دوہراندا	VBF	O
رہندا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
اس	PRP	O
لئی	PSP	O
ہے	VBF	O
لوکاں	NN	O
اندر	NN	O
آپنے	APNA	O
ساتھی	NN	O
ناگرکاں	NN	O
پرتی	PSP	O
ہمدردی	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پھیر	RB	O
ہور	Q	O
دوست	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

ساری	JJ	O
دنیا	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
دس	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
گیتا	NN	PER
نوں	PSP	O
اپنی	APNA	O
دھی	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
لیا	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہدے	PRS	O
مگروں	PSP	O
میں	PRP	O
ہر	JJ	O
بندے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
پہلے	OD	O
ایلس	NNP	PER
کول	PSP	O
بھیجدا	VBF	O
رقم	NN	O
دین	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
جد	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
پلائی	VBF	O
وڈ	NNP	O
دی	PSP	O
کندھ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
پاروں	PSP	O
سبھ	Q	O
اچھاکہہ	VBF	O
دیندی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
میں	PRP	O
فیض	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
غزل	NN	O
اوس	PDM	O
بندے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
پھڑا	VBF	O
دیندا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

جے	SCP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
گلی	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بندہ	NN	O
سچی	JJ	O
گل	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
تے	SC	O
ایویں	PRP	O
بھونڈاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کھکھر	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہتھ	NN	O
دین	VBI	O
والی	VALA	O
گل	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اتے	SCP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
پڑھن	VBI	O
والے	VALA	O
محبوب	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
فکری	JJ	O
زلفاں	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
مینڈھیاں	NN	O
سواردیاں	VBF	O
ہین	AUXT	O
اوہنا	Q	O
ندے	JJ	O
جوہری	JJ	O
حظیریاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
احساس	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
ولاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ساہتی	JJ	O
پریرنا	NN	O
پن	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دیاں	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

منشاء	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
ءوچ	PSP	O
بھٹو	NNP	PER
ہوراں	INJ	O
دی	PSP	O
نیشنلائزیشن	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
چنگی	JJ	O
مار	NN	O
پئی	VBF	O
پر	SC	O
نواز	NNP	PER
شریف	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
ڈی	NNP	O
نیشنلائزیشن	NNP	O
پاروں	PSP	O
چوکھا	Q	O
اپاہ	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

وارث	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
وی	PRT	O
ہیر	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
روح	NN	O
تے	CC	O
رانجھے	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
قلبوت	NNP	O
آکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
دسیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
ہیر	NNP	PER
تے	CC	O
رانجھا	NNP	PER
دراصل	RB	O
اک	CD	O
وجود	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
دو	CD	O
ٹوٹے	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
جیہڑے	PRR	O
مڑ	NN	O
اک	CD	O
ہو	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
اپنی	APNA	O
تکمیل	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
خواہش	NN	O
کردے	VBF	O
ہیر	NNP	PER
روح	NN	O
تے	CC	O
رانجھے	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
قلبوت	NN	O
منیے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اک	CD	O
ہور	Q	O
گل	NN	O
تیکر	PSP	O
سوچ	NN	O
اپڑدی	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
جے	SC	O
بندے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
مادی	JJ	O
وجود	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
اصل	JJ	O
روح	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
کیوں	RB	O
جے	SC	O
روح	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
تعلق	NN	O
ازلی	JJ	O
روح	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میری	PRS	O
سوکن	NN	O
امید	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ہوئی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
بہوں	Q	O
خوشیاں	NN	O
منائیاں	VBF	O
گئیاں	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

جے	SCP	O
کتے	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
اک	CD	O
قدم	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
ایدھر	NN	O
اودھر	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
تاں	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
بھنجے	NN	O
جا	VBF	O
پوے	AUXA	O
گی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

انکل	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
میرے	PRS	O
سوہرے	NN	O
مینوں	PRP	O
بہت	Q	O
تنگ	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جس	PRR	O
وچ	PSP	O
سارے	JJ	O
پاسے	NN	O
بسنت	NN	O
بارے	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
لکھیا	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

دوہاں	OD	O
دے	PSP	O
ویاہ	NN	O
اینی	Q	O
شانتی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ہوئے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
کسے	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
یقین	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
نہ	NEG	O
آیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اٹھی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
وائن	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
پوری	JJ	O
بوتل	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
گلاس	NN	O
لے	VBF	O
آئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

پنجابی	NNP	O
نال	PSP	O
جو	PRR	O
ان	PRE	O
حق	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
پنجابی	JJ	O
لکھاریاں	NN	O
ہر	JJ	O
سمے	NN	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
سوال	NN	O
اٹھایا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
سبھ	Q	O
یاد	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کرنٹ	NN	O
اکاونٹ	NN	O
خسارہ	NN	O
جی	NNP	O
ڈی	NNP	O
پی	NNP	O
دا	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
فیصد	JJ	O
رہن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
امکان	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
جیہدی	PRS	O
وجہ	NN	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
اے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
ترسیلات	JJ	O
زر	NN	O
تے	CC	O
برآمدات	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وادھا	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
لگیا	VBF	O
جیویں	PRR	O
اوہ	PRP	O
لنگڑی	JJ	O
ہے	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
امن	NN	O
اک	CD	O
لاٹھی	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جس	PRR	O
دے	PSP	O
سہارے	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
کھڑی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
جاں	CC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
اک	CD	O
اجیہی	PDM	O
چکنی	JJ	O
بھومی	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جتھے	NN	O
صرف	JJ	O
امن	NN	O
ہی	PRT	O
اوس	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
سہارا	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پاکستان	NNP	LOC
دے	PSP	O
حوالے	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
خبر	NN	O
زیادہ	Q	O
ماڑی	JJ	O
نہیں	NEG	O
لگدی	VBF	O
کیوں	RB	O
جے	SC	O
ایتھے	NN	O
سوائے	PRE	O
سرکاری	JJ	O
افسراں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کوئی	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
نہ	NEG	O
تے	PRT	O
پورا	JJ	O
ٹیکس	NN	O
دیندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
نہ	NEG	O
ای	PRT	O
ایہدے	PRS	O
بارے	PSP	O
بھرواں	JJ	O
ریکارڈ	NN	O
رکھن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
کھیچل	NN	O
کردا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ڈونٹ	CD	O
بی	NNP	O
سلی	NNP	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
تینوں	PRP	O
لبھ	VBF	O
لبھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
کملی	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
آں	AUXT	O
تیرے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
بڑی	JJ	O
ضروری	JJ	O
گل	NN	O
کرنی	VBI	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اپنے	APNA	O
دیس	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کھیت	NN	O
کھلیان	NN	O
،	PU	O
باغ	NN	O
میدان	NN	O
ڈھولے	NN	O
ٹپے	JJ	O
ماہیے	JJ	O
گدے	JJ	O
بولیاں	NN	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
کملیاں	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
دیندے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
گنڈھ	NN	O
سوچ	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کھل	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
پھو	NN	O
کنا	Q	O
جوانی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
جیہڑی	PRR	O
دیس	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
بھل	VBF	O
جاوے	AUXA	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

ملک	NN	PER
نے	PSP	PER
اتوں	NN	O
رتی	JJ	O
اوہدیاں	PRS	O
پنج	CD	O
پتنگاں	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
دتیاں	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
شاماں	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
بانگاں	NN	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
ای	PRT	O
دوہاں	OD	O
نے	PSP	O
پتنگاں	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
لتیاں	AUXA	O
ملک	NN	PER
نماز	NN	PER
پڑھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
بھا	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
ہوراں	INJ	O
کول	PSP	O
شاواشی	NNP	O
لیون	NNP	O
آ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

‫	RB	O
سپریم	JJ	ORG
کورٹ	NN	ORG
وچ	PSP	O
علماء	NN	O
ہند	NNP	O
دا	PSP	O
بیان	NN	O
بھارت	NNP	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
کڑیاں	NN	O
پھاہے	NN	O
کیوں	RB	O
چڑھ	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
نیں	AUXT	O
وچوں	PSP	O
وچوں	PSP	O
اتوں	NN	O
اتوں	NN	O
الیکشن	NN	O
۲۰۱۳	CD	O
مسلم	NNP	ORG
لیگ	NNP	ORG
ن	NNP	ORG
جے	NNP	ORG
یو	NNP	ORG
آئی	NNP	ORG
ان	PRE	O
پر	SC	O
جماعت	NN	O
کیوں	RB	O
نہیں	NEG	O
؟	PU	O

تھوڑے	Q	O
چر	NN	O
مگروں	PSP	O
ای	PRT	O
مینوں	PRP	O
نیندر	NN	O
آون	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پئی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

نصیبو	NNP	PER
اوہ	PRP	O
لسی	NN	O
رڑکدیاں	VBF	O
سار	PRT	O
ای	PRT	O
کسے	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
باہر	NN	O
چلی	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کئی	Q	O
تھاواں	NN	O
تے	CC	O
وچ	PSP	O
وچ	PSP	O
گجراں	NN	O
مجھاں	NN	O
رکھیاں	VBF	O
ہوئیاں	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

لے	VBF	O
کوئی	PRP	O
دسدا	VBF	O
تھوڑی	Q	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

دادو	NNP	PER
گالھڑ	NNP	PER
دا	PSP	O
بیلی	NN	O
دیوی	NN	PER
لال	JJ	PER
سنیارا	NN	PER
۔	PU	O

اتے	SCP	O
پھٹیاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
پائے	VBF	O
کیڑے	NN	O
مکوڑے	VBF	O
ویکھ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
خوش	JJ	O
ہوندیاں	VBF	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
والاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
انگلاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کنگھی	NN	O
پھیردیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

دوسرے	OD	O
نے	PSP	O
بھاویں	RB	O
کوئی	PDM	O
کم	NN	O
کنا	Q	O
وی	PRT	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
تے	PRT	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
سوچدا	VBF	O
پیاںجے	AUXT	O
بابا	NN	PER
بلھے	NNP	PER
شاہ	NNP	PER
ہوراں	INJ	O
نوںاپنی	PSP	O
پنجابی	JJ	O
بولی	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
ای	PRT	O
شہر	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
دھیاں	NN	O
پتر	NN	O
اںدے	PRS	O
مونہوں	NN	O
گاہل	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
کناں	JJ	O
دکھ	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
ہووے	AUXA	O
گا	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

حکومت	NN	O
جدوں	NN	O
اندرون	JJ	O
ملک	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
بہتے	Q	O
قرضے	NN	O
لیندے	VBF	O
ای	AUXT	O
تاں	SC	O
افراط	JJ	O
زر	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
دباء	NN	O
شدت	NN	O
اختیار	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
جاندا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
کرنسی	NN	O
نوٹ	NN	O
کاغذ	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
پرزے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
بدلدا	VBF	O
جاندا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
نجی	JJ	O
شعبے	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
سرمایا	NN	O
کاری	NN	O
سرگرمیاں	NN	O
جمود	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
شکار	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
جاندیاں	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
لوکاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
معاشی	JJ	O
حالت	NN	O
زار	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
وادھا	NN	O
ہوندا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
معیشت	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
تباہی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
دروازے	NN	O
کھلدے	VBF	O
جاندے	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پتہ	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ماں	NN	O
بھین	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
کیہ	RB	O
سکھایا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
کدوں	NN	O
انہاں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
راٹھ	NN	O
بنایا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اصلی	JJ	O
مدعے	NN	O
ولوں	PSP	O
پچھے	NN	O
ہٹ	VBF	O
جاندے	AUXA	O
ہن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

وزیر	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
ایس	PDM	O
خبر	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
سخت	JJ	O
نوٹس	NN	O
لیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
ایف	NNP	ORG
بی	NNP	ORG
آر	NNP	ORG
دے	PSP	O
وچوں	PSP	O
افسراں	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
ٹیکس	NN	O
گوشوارے	NN	O
جمع	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
کرائے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ضروری	JJ	O
گل	NN	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
اے	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
ایس	PDM	O
پوری	JJ	O
ریاست	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سوانیاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
آبادی	NN	O
پنج	CD	O
لکھ	CD	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اخیر	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
پھیر	RB	O
ایل	NNP	ORG
ڈی	NNP	ORG
اے	NNP	ORG
تے	CC	O
کارپوریشن	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
گڈیاں	NN	O
کنے	Q	O
ڈھیر	JJ	O
سارے	JJ	O
بندے	NN	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دے	PSP	O
پچھے	NN	O
پچھے	NN	O
رولا	NN	O
پاندے	VBF	O
آوندے	VBF	O
پئے	AUXP	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پھتے	NNP	PER
حرامدے	NNP	PER
دارو	NN	O
کھروی	JJ	O
اواز	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
کہیا	VBF	O
نوری	NNP	PER
بی	NNP	PER
بی	NNP	PER
،	PU	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
تیرا	PRS	O
گلا	NN	O
س	NN	O
باہر	NN	O
پیا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تانبے	NN	O
داایہہ	PSP	O
نواں	JJ	O
قلعی	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
گلاس	NN	O
اوس	PDM	O
سویرے	NN	O
نوری	NNP	PER
بی	NNP	PER
بی	NNP	PER
صغراں	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
دتاسی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
کیویں	RB	O
وگاں	NN	O
۔	PU	O

بس	RB	O
کدی	NN	O
کدی	NN	O
انج	PRP	O
ہونا	VBI	O
کہ	SC	O
ساڈی	PRS	O
گل	NN	O
مک	VBF	O
جانی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تہاڈا	PRS	O
گھر	NN	O
سگاڑی	JJ	LOC
موہڑے	NN	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
اے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

سدھا	JJ	O
بھارت	NNP	LOC
گھل	VBF	O
دتا	AUXA	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اپنے	APNA	O
خاندا	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
کول	PSP	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

قومی	JJ	O
دولت	NN	O
تے	CC	O
اقتدار	NN	O
برہمناں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ہتھ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
ددھ	NN	O
پیندا	VBF	O
بچہ	NN	O
ہاں	VBF	O
جو	PRR	O
امی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
پچھاں	VBF	O
گا	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
شادی	NN	O
کراں	VBF	O
جاں	CC	O
ناں	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

جے	SCP	O
سرخی	NN	O
بنن	VBI	O
ای	PRT	O
جانا	VBI	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	SC	O
فیر	RB	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

فیر	RB	O
اوہ	PRP	O
کلکتہ	NNP	LOC
واپس	NN	O
چلے	VBF	O
گئے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

پنجابی	JJ	O
اکھان	NN	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PRP	O
میریاں	PRS	O
مہربانیاں	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
جو	PRR	O
اج	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
ایس	PDM	O
پوزیشن	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہیں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

عالمی	JJ	ORG
صحت	NN	ORG
ادارے	NN	ORG
موجب	PSP	O
پورے	JJ	O
سنسار	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ہر	JJ	O
سال	NN	O
قریب	NN	O
لکھ	CD	O
لوک	NN	O
خودکشی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
مردے	VBF	O
ہن	AUXT	O
جس	PRR	O
نال	PSP	O
سالانہ	JJ	O
٫	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
حساب	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
لکھ	CD	O
دی	PSP	O
در	NN	O
بیٹھدی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
کیوں	RB	O
چکاں	VBF	O
اوس	PRP	O
مریا	VBF	O
چوہا	NN	O
میں	PRP	O
کیہہ	RB	O
گناہ	NN	O
کیتا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
؟	PU	O

جاری	JJ	O
جے	SC	O
ایہہ	PDM	O
مادھو	NN	PER
لعل	NNP	PER
حسین	NNP	PER
لہور	NNP	LOC
دی	PSP	O
ویل	NN	O
ناول	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
حصہ	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
جیہڑا	PRR	O
لڑی	CD	O
وار	NN	O
وچار	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
لکھاری	NN	O
آپوں	PRF	O
دتای	VBF	O
جے	PRX	O
۔	PU	O

میں	PRP	O
تینوں	PRP	O
کنا	Q	O
سمجھایا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
کہ	SC	O
اوہ	PDM	O
ٹبر	NN	O
قصائیاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ہے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بختاں	NN	PER
بخاریاں	NN	PER
توں	PSP	O
ہی	PRT	O
گھیو	NN	O
چا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
چھوہر	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
دتا	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
ساجا	NN	PER
نائی	NN	PER
ولے	PSP	O
دڑکی	NN	O
لا	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PDM	O
وڈیری	JJ	O
عمر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
مائی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
کلیاں	NN	O
کاہنوں	RB	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پی	NNP	LOC
وچ	PSP	O
کیمونسٹ	NN	ORG
پارٹی	NN	ORG
دے	PSP	O
سیکرٹری	NN	O
جنرل	NN	O
ہندے	VBF	O
سن	AUXT	O
نواب	NN	PER
جعفر	NNP	PER
۔	PU	O

توں	PRP	O
اداس	JJ	O
تاں	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
کتے	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
؟	PU	O

رلویں	JJ	O
صلاح	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
رول	NN	O
فالکن	NNP	PER
ہوراں	INJ	O
نوں	PSP	O
کھیڈن	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
آکھیا	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ایہو	PRP	O
جیہا	PRR	O
ہی	PRT	O
سی	VBF	O
اک	CD	O
انڈین	JJ	O
منڈا	NN	O
۔	PU	O

ایس	PRP	O
وچ	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
شک	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سینما	NN	O
گھمبیر	JJ	O
سماجی	JJ	O
مسلیاں	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
نجھٹدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
روشن	JJ	O
خیالی	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ورتارے	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
حل	NN	O
دسدا	VBF	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

میاں	NN	PER
صاحبؒ	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
کلام	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ایس	PDM	O
فانی	JJ	O
دنیا	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
بے	JJ	O
ثباتی	NN	O
بارے	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
کنے	Q	O
ای	PRT	O
شعر	NN	O
ملدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

سالے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
بھانڈے	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
وکوا	VBF	O
دتے	AUXA	O
تاں	SC	O
دتہ	NNP	PER
نہ	NEG	O
کہیں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کدے	NN	O
میں	PRP	O
کوڑا	NN	O
سٹن	VBI	O
دے	PSP	O
بہانے	NN	O
گلی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
آوندی	VBF	O
کدے	NN	O
گھر	NN	O
موہرے	NN	O
لگے	VBF	O
نلکے	NN	O
توں	PSP	O
پانی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
بالٹی	NN	O
بھرن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
پکھنڈ	NN	O
کردی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کدی	NN	O
آنی	VBI	O
بہانی	JJ	O
گوانڈھیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
گھروں	NN	O
دال	NN	O
پچھن	VBI	O
چلی	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

کرم	NNP	O
علی	NNP	O
کیفی	NNP	O
نال	PSP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
میرا	PRS	O
پہلا	OD	O
تعارف	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
جیہڑا	PRR	O
عنایت	NNP	PER
حسین	NNP	PER
بھٹی	NNP	PER
دے	PSP	O
ذریعے	PSP	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

شریف	NNP	PER
نانا	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
؟	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
پڑھائی	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
نہ	NEG	O
چل	VBF	O
سکی	AUXM	O
کیوں	RB	O
کہ	SC	O
جتھے	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
پڑھن	VBI	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
ماسٹر	NN	O
تے	CC	O
ماسٹرانیاں	NN	O
اوس	PRP	O
توں	PSP	O
گھر	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
کم	NN	O
کروا	VBF	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
دے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

دھوتی	NN	O
اچی	JJ	O
کرکے	PSP	O
لنگوٹ	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
لیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

انسانی	JJ	O
حقاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
احترام	NN	O
پاروں	PSP	O
اساں	PRP	O
انسانی	JJ	O
خشیاں	NN	O
معاشریاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
مضبوطیاں	NN	O
اتے	CC	O
تیزی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
دوجے	OD	O
نال	PSP	O
جڑ	VBF	O
چکی	AUXA	O
دنیا	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
مک	VBF	O
ہون	AUXA	O
وچ	PSP	O
مدد	NN	O
دیندے	VBF	O
ہاں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

رب	NNP	O
دا	PSP	O
گھر	NN	O
بنا	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
رب	NNP	O
نوں	PSP	O
خوش	JJ	O
کیتا	VBF	O
جے	PRX	O
ہن	NN	O
رب	NNP	O
دے	PSP	O
بندیاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
خوش	JJ	O
کرو	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
اوہناں	PRP	O
دیاں	PSP	O
دعاواں	NN	O
لوو	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جیہڑے	PRD	O
سوال	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
جواب	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
اوہدے	PRS	O
وچ	PSP	O
بائوہردیال	VBF	PER
نوں	PSP	O
شمسی	NNP	PER
صاحب	NN	PER
راہیں	PSP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
پچھیا	VBF	O
د	AUXT	O
دس	CD	O
کھاں	NN	O
شہر	NN	O
لہور	NNP	LOC
اندر	NN	O
بئی	SC	O
کنے	Q	O
بوہے	NN	O
تے	CC	O
کنیاں	Q	O
باریاں	NN	O
نیں	VBF	O
نالے	PSP	O
دس	CD	O
کھاں	NN	O
اوتھوں	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
اٹاں	NN	O
کنیاں	Q	O
ٹٹیاں	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
کنیاں	Q	O
ساریاں	JJ	O
نیں	VBF	O
د	NNP	O
دس	CD	O
کھاں	VBF	O
شہر	NN	O
لہور	NNP	LOC
اندر	NN	O
کھوہیاں	NN	O
کنیاں	Q	O
مٹھیاں	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کنیاں	Q	O
کھاریاں	JJ	O
نیں	VBF	O
ذرا	JJ	O
سوچ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
دیویں	VBF	O
جواب	NN	O
مینوں	PRP	O
اوتھے	NN	O
کنیاں	Q	O
ویاہیاں	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
کنیاں	Q	O
کواریاں	JJ	O
نیں	VBF	O
ہفتہ	CD	O
اپریل	NNP	O
بھاء	NNP	O
جی	INJ	O
دے	PSP	O
مسلم	JJ	O
لیگی	JJ	O
دوست	NN	O
شاہ	NNP	PER
جی	INJ	PER
ملتان	NNP	LOC
دے	PSP	O
کوئی	PDM	O
وڈے	JJ	O
زمین	NN	O
دار	JJ	O
کسے	PDM	O
مقدمے	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
مشورے	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
مینوں	PRP	O
ملن	VBI	O
آئے	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

ساری	JJ	O
رات	NN	O
اوسے	PRP	O
کول	PSP	O
رہی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

نالے	PRE	O
رکھاں	NN	O
بارے	PSP	O
کتاب	NN	O
۔	PU	O

مملوکہ	NN	O
محمد	NNP	PER
علی	NNP	PER
چراغ	JJ	PER
پتر	NN	O
چراغ	NN	PER
دین	NNP	PER
جونے	VBF	PER
کے	SCK	PER
والا	VALA	PER
۔	PU	O

مڑہکو	NN	O
مڑکی	VBF	O
ہوئیاں	AUXA	O
سواریاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
سریراں	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
نکلدی	VBF	O
ہواڑ	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
اوس	PRP	O
دا	PSP	O
ساہ	NN	O
لینا	VBI	O
اوکھا	JJ	O
کر	VBF	O
چھڈیا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
نک	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
رومال	NN	O
دھری	VBF	O
اک	CD	O
انگریزی	JJ	O
ناول	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
نوں	PSP	O
بھلاون	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
کوشش	NN	O
کر	VBF	O
رہی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

پرویزجد	NNP	PER
مزدور	NN	ORG
کسان	NN	ORG
پارٹی	NN	ORG
ٹٹی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
تسی	PRP	O
کلو	NNP	O
ہوراں	INJ	O
دے	PSP	O
نال	PSP	O
رہے	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

ہر	JJ	O
پنج	CD	O
دن	NN	O
بعد	NN	O
یا	CC	O
چھ	CD	O
دن	NN	O
بعد	NN	O
اک	CD	O
دھماکہ	NN	O
ضرور	RB	O
ہونا	VBI	O
ہوندا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
میری	PRS	O
کمر	NN	O
دوالے	NN	O
بانہاں	NN	O
کسیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوہنوں	PRP	O
اپنے	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
تے	PSP	O
کنا	Q	O
اعتماد	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
مینوں	PRP	O
ڈراپ	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
توں	PSP	O
بعد	NN	O
جدوں	NN	O
جاون	VBI	O
لگا	AUXA	O
تے	CC	O
بولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

میراسلام	NNP	O
آکھنا	VBI	O
اوہنوں	PRP	O
۔	PU	O

اوہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
جامی	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
کتاب	NN	O
یوسف	NNP	O
زلیخا	NNP	O
سنن	VBI	O
دا	PSP	O
بوہت	Q	O
شوق	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پر	SCP	O
کدے	NN	O
نرا	JJ	O
مال	NN	O
اسباب	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
لد	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
لیاوندیاں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایہہ	PDM	O
سیوا	NN	O
تے	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

پورے	JJ	O
دا	PSP	O
پورا	JJ	O
علاقہ	NN	O
پولیس	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
خلاف	JJ	O
ہو	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

جمال	NNP	PER
دی	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
بھین	NN	O
تے	CC	O
اک	CD	O
بھرا	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

جد	NN	O
نہال	NNP	PER
مسیح	NNP	PER
نوں	PSP	O
پتا	NN	O
لگا	VBF	O
تاں	SC	O
اوہ	PRP	O
سبھ	Q	O
کم	NN	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
آ	VBF	O
گیا	AUXA	O
اتے	CC	O
بھائیا	NN	O
جی	INJ	O
دیاں	PSP	O
لتاں	NN	O
گھٹن	VBI	O
لگ	AUXA	O
پیا	AUXA	O
۔	PU	O

تیریاں	PRS	O
اکھاں	NN	O
نروئے	JJ	O
سفنیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ادم	NN	O
تے	CC	O
حیاتی	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
جانن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
حیرانی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
وتر	NN	O
سن	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ڈوبیل	NN	O
دتی	VBF	O
کسے	PDM	O
خوبصورت	JJ	O
عورت	NN	O
نے	PSP	O
دروازہ	NN	O
کھولیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

بھا	NNP	O
جی	INJ	O
سگریٹ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
اک	CD	O
لما	JJ	O
سوٹا	NN	O
بھر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
بولے	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ایتھے	NN	O
سوال	NN	O
پیدا	NN	O
ہوندااے	VBF	O
پئی	SC	O
کلچر	NN	O
یا	CC	O
ثقافت	NN	O
کس	PDM	O
شئے	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
آکھدے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
انسانی	JJ	O
حیاتی	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
ایہدا	PRS	O
کیہ	RB	O
سمبندھ	NN	O
اے	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

پل	NN	O
بناون	VBI	O
واسطے	PSP	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
نوں	PSP	O
اٹاں	NN	O
لوڑی	VBF	O
دیاں	AUXA	O
سن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہدا	PRS	O
پنجرہ	NN	O
کھلا	VBF	O
ای	PRT	O
رہندا	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

عامر	NNP	PER
بھارت	NNP	PER
وچ	PSP	O
وی	PRT	O
سیکولرازم	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
رام	NNP	PER
راجیہ	NNP	PER
فٹ	RB	O
ہے	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

گیتا	NNP	PER
کمبی	VBF	O
جا	AUXA	O
رہی	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اکو	CD	O
چیز	NN	O
اکساندی	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
میں	PRP	O
پڑھنا	VBI	O
ضرور	RB	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہنے	PRP	O
کمانڈر	NN	O
نوںآکھیا	VBF	O
کہ	SC	O
پتہ	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
ایسدی	PRS	O
شریعی	JJ	O
حیثیت	NN	O
کی	PSP	O
ایہہ	PRP	O
تے	PRT	O
کی	RB	O
نیئں	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

اوس	PRP	O
نے	PSP	O
لما	JJ	O
ہنگورا	NN	O
بھریا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

خالداتے	INJ	PER
جدوں	NN	O
کانگرس	NNP	ORG
تے	CC	O
مسلم	JJ	ORG
لیگ	NN	ORG
بنیاں	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

ایہناں	PDM	O
سچائیاں	NN	O
والے	VALA	O
اکھان	NN	O
ناقابل	JJ	O
تردید	NN	O
صداقتاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
علمبردار	NN	O
ہوندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اک	CD	O
دن	NN	O
میرے	PRS	O
کول	PSP	O
سگرٹاں	NN	O
لئی	PSP	O
پیسے	NN	O
نہیں	NEG	O
سن	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
میں	PRP	O
ایہناں	PDM	O
تیراں	CD	O
راپیاں	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
گن	VBF	O
رہیاسی	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ہن	NN	O
اوہ	PRP	O
اپنیاں	APNA	O
ڈاہڈیاں	JJ	O
میلیاں	JJ	O
اکھاں	NN	O
پورے	JJ	O
زور	NN	O
نال	PSP	O
کھول	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
بلیڈ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ٹوٹا	NN	O
وکھاندیاں	VBF	O
ہوئیاں	AUXA	O
گاہلاں	NN	O
کڈھ	VBF	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اتوں	NN	O
گولیاں	NN	O
لنگھدیاں	VBF	O
رہندیاں	AUXP	O
نیں	AUXT	O
اسیں	PRP	O
لوگ	NN	O
ویڑھے	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
بیٹھے	VBF	O
ہونے	AUXA	O
آں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

اوہ	PRP	O
اٹھ	CD	O
دن	NN	O
سوہریاں	NN	O
تے	PSP	O
ہوندی	VBF	O
تے	SC	O
دو	CD	O
مہینے	NN	O
ایتھے	NN	O
۔	PU	O

بڑا	JJ	O
سوہنا	JJ	O
دن	NN	O
سی	VBF	O
تے	CC	O
ادھ	FR	O
مگھر	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
دھپ	NN	O
تے	CC	O
مٹھامٹھا	JJ	O
نگھ	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
سواد	NN	O
۔	PU	O

کنی	Q	O
دیر	NN	O
اسیں	PRP	O
چپ	NN	O
بیٹھے	VBF	O
رہنا	AUXP	O
تے	CC	O
توں	PRP	O
ہولی	RB	O
جیہی	PRT	O
ہوکا	NN	O
بھر	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
آکھنا	VBI	O
۔	PU	O

جیون	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
پینڈا	NN	O
کسے	PRP	O
وی	PRT	O
گھبرو	NN	O
جوان	JJ	O
ہار	NN	O
میرا	PRS	O
وی	PRT	O
ویاہ	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

ہن	NN	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
عمر	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
ااوہ	JJ	O
حصہ	NN	O
ہے	VBF	O
بئی	SC	O
ایہناں	PRP	O
دی	PSP	O
خدمت	NN	O
کرن	VBI	O
لئی	PSP	O
کوئی	PRP	O
ہونا	VBI	O
چاہیدا	AUXM	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

بڑے	JJ	O
لوکاں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

وڈیاں	JJ	O
دا	PSP	O
کہنا	VBI	O
منی	VBF	O
دا	PSP	O
۔	PU	O

اپنیاں	APNA	O
دو	CD	O
چھوٹیاں	JJ	O
بھیناں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
کلی	JJ	O
امید	NN	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

اصل	JJ	O
ملن	VBI	O
تاں	PRT	O
اج	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

کڑیاں	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ماں	NN	O
پیو	NN	O
تینوں	PRP	O
دعاواں	NN	O
دیندے	VBF	O
نیں	AUXT	O
تینوں	PRP	O
ہور	Q	O
کیہ	RB	O
چاہیدا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

منڈا	NN	O
ساڈے	PRS	O
کول	PSP	O
اپڑگیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

کریں	VBF	O
توکل	NN	O
رب	NNP	O
سچے	JJ	O
تے	CC	O
لاہ	VBF	O
دنیا	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
جھاک	NN	O
چھڈ	VBF	O
کے	SCK	O
لالچ	NN	O
لوبھ	NN	O
نوں	PSP	O
توں	PRP	O
اوئے	PU	O
رکھ	VBF	O
محبت	NN	O
پاک	NN	O
کدے	NN	O
نہ	NEG	O
چھڈیں	VBF	O
دوستا	NN	O
پنجہیں	CD	O
یار	NN	O
پنجاہیں	CD	O
ساک	NN	O
پنجابی	NNP	O
دے	PSP	O
بے	NN	O
شمار	NN	O
اکھاناں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
عالمگیر	JJ	O
سچائیاں	NN	O
وی	PRT	O
بھریاں	VBF	O
ہوندیاں	AUXA	O
نیں	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

خوش	JJ	O
رہن	VBI	O
دی	PSP	O
پدھر	NN	O
ء	SYM	O
توں	PSP	O
ء	SYM	O
تیکر	PSP	O
دنیا	NN	O
دے	PSP	O
ملکاں	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
ودھی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
تے	CC	O
رہندے	VBF	O
وچ	PSP	O
گھٹی	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ٹھیک	JJ	O
اتے	CC	O
پورن	NN	O
گیان	NN	O
رکھن	VBI	O
نال	PSP	O
آدمی	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
زندگی	NN	O
وچوں	PSP	O
بہت	Q	O
مشکلاں	NN	O
آپنے	APNA	O
آپ	PRF	O
ختم	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
جاندیاں	AUXA	O
ہن	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

انو	NN	PER
جیویں	PRR	O
ہلکی	JJ	O
ہونی	VBI	O
شروع	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
گئی	AUXA	O
سی	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

مقبولیت	NN	O
سر	NN	O
ناویں	NN	O
ریکارڈ	NN	O
توڑ	JJ	O
ثابت	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

دو	CD	O
مہینے	NN	O
بعد	NN	O
ولیتوں	NN	LOC
منوں	NN	O
دلے	NN	PER
دا	PSP	O
خط	NN	O
آیا	VBF	O
۔	PU	O

پنجاب	JJ	LOC
کہانی	NN	O
انگریز	NN	O
پنجاب	NNP	LOC
تے	PSP	O
قبضہ	NN	O
کیوں	RB	O
کیتا	VBF	O
؟	PU	O

دس	CD	O
پونڈ	NN	O
وچ	PSP	O
تیویں	NN	O
مل	VBF	O
جاندی	AUXA	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	SYM	O
۔	PU	O

میری	PRS	O
عورت	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
میرے	PRS	O
نال	PSP	O
ویاہ	NN	O
ہویا	VBF	O
ہے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

ساڈے	PRS	O
وسیب	NN	O
دیاں	PSP	O
موتیاں	NN	O
ورگیاں	PRR	O
انملیاں	JJ	O
قدراں	NN	O
دا	PSP	O
بھنڈار	NN	O
ہولے	JJ	O
ہولے	NN	O
گھٹدا	VBF	O
جا	AUXA	O
رہیا	AUXP	O
اے	AUXT	O
۔	PU	O

چل	VBF	O
دفعہ	NN	O
ہو	VBF	O
جا	AUXA	O
ایتھوں	NN	O
سانوں	PRP	O
تیرے	PRS	O
جیہے	PRR	O
گاہکاں	NN	O
دی	PSP	O
لوڑ	NN	O
ای	PRT	O
نہیں	NEG	O
۔	PU	O

